<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/master/src/out/critical.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/master/src/out/critical.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Elements, Book 12</title>
        <author>Euclid</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Elements, Book 12</title>
          <date when="2014-03-19">March 03, 2014</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a <ref target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs 3.0 License</ref></p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="X" n="xxx"/>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-critical-1.0.0" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/master/src/out/critical.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0 
          guidelines for a critical edition.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2014-03-19" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>File Started for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="la">
    <front>
      
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="ee-b12" n="1">
        <head xml:id="ee-b12-Hd1e3715">BOOK XII.</head>
        <head xml:id="ee-b12-Hd1e3718">HISTORICAL NOTE.</head>
        <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e3721"> The predominant feature of Book XII. is the use of the <hi rend="ital">method of
            exhaustion</hi> , which is applied in Propositions <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e3726" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.12.2">2</ref> , <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e3729" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.12.3 elem.12.4 elem.12.5">3-5</ref> , <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e3732" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.12.10 elem.12.11 elem.12.12">10, 11, 12</ref> , and (in a
          slightly different form) in <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e3735" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.12.16 elem.12.17 elem.12.18">Propositions 16-18</ref> . We conclude therefore that for the content of this Book
          Euclid was greatly indebted to Eudoxus, to whom the discovery of the method of exhaustion
          is attributed. The evidence for this attribution comes mainly from Archimedes. (1) In the
          preface to <title>On the Sphere and Cylinder</title> I., after stating the main results
          obtained by himself regarding the surface of a sphere or a segment thereof, and the volume
          and surface of a right cylinder with height equal to its diameter as compared with those
          of a sphere with the same diameter, Archimedes adds: <quote xml:id="ee-b12-Qd1e3742"> Having now discovered that
            the properties mentioned are true of these figures, I cannot feel any hesitation in
            setting them side by side both with my former investigations and <hi rend="ital">with
              those of the theorems of Eudoxus on solids</hi> which are held to be most irrefragably
            established, namely that <hi rend="ital"> any pyramid is one third part of the prism
              which has the same base with the pyramid and equal height </hi> [i.e. Eucl. <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e3750" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.12.7">XII. 7</ref> ], and that <hi rend="ital"> any cone is
              one third part of the cylinder which has the same base with the cone and equal height
            </hi> [i.e. Eucl. <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e3756" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.12.10">XII. 10</ref> ]. For, though
            these properties also were naturally inherent in the figures all along, yet they were in
            fact unknown to all the many able geometers who lived before Eudoxus and had not been
            observed by any one. </quote> (2) In the preface to the treatise known as the
            <title>Quadrature of the Parabola</title> Archimedes states the <quote xml:id="ee-b12-Qd1e3763">lemma</quote>
          assumed by him and known as the <quote xml:id="ee-b12-Qd1e3766">Axiom of Archimedes</quote> (see note on <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e3769" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.10.1">X. 1</ref> above) and proceeds: <quote xml:id="ee-b12-Qd1e3773"> Earlier
            geometers ( <foreign xml:lang="greek">οἱ πρότερον γεωμέτραι</foreign> ) have also used this
            lemma; for it is by the use of this same lemma that they have shown that <hi rend="ital"> circles are to one another in the duplicate ratio of their diameters </hi> [Eucl.
              <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e3781" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.12.2">XII. 2</ref> ], and that <hi rend="ital">
              spheres are to one another in the triplicate ratio of their diameters </hi> [Eucl.
              <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e3787" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.12.18">XII. 18</ref> ], and further that <hi rend="ital"> every pyramid is one third part of the prism which has the same base with
              the pyramid and equal height </hi> [Eucl. <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e3794" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.12.7">XII.
              7</ref> ]; also, that <hi rend="ital"> every cone is one third part of the cylinder
              which has the same base with the cone and equal height </hi> [Eucl. <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e3800" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.12.10">XII. 10</ref> ] they proved by assuming <hi rend="ital">a certain lemma similar to that aforesaid</hi> . </quote> Thus in the
          first passage two theorems of Eucl. XII. are definitely attributed to Eudoxus; and, when
          Archimedes says, in the second passage, that <quote xml:id="ee-b12-Qd1e3807">earlier geometers</quote> proved these
          two theorems by means of the lemma known as the <quote xml:id="ee-b12-Qd1e3810">Axiom of Archimedes</quote> and of
          a lemma similar to it respectively, we can hardly suppose him to be alluding to  any other proof than that given by Eudoxus. As a matter of fact, the lemma
          used by Euclid to prove both propositions ( <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e3813" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.12.3 elem.12.4 elem.12.5">XII. 3-5</ref> and <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e3816" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.12.7">7</ref> , and
            <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e3819" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.12.10">XII. 10</ref> ) is the theorem of Eucl. <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e3823" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.10.1">X. 1</ref> . As regards the connexion between the two
            <quote xml:id="ee-b12-Qd1e3826">lemmas</quote> see note on <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e3829" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.10.1">X. 1</ref> . </p>
        <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e3833"> We are not, however, to suppose that none of the <hi rend="ital">results</hi> obtained
          by the method of exhaustion had been discovered before the time of Eudoxus (fl. about
          368-5 B.C.). Two at least are of earlier date, those of <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e3838" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.12.2">Eucl. XII. 2</ref> and <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e3841" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.12.7">XII. 7</ref>
          . </p>
        <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e3845"> （ <hi rend="ital">a</hi> ) Simplicius ( <title>Comment. in Aristot. Phys.</title> p. 61,
          ed. Diels) quotes Eudemus as saying, in his <title>History of Geometry</title> , that
          Hippocrates of Chios (fl. say 430 B.C.) first laid it down ( <foreign xml:lang="greek">ἔθετο</foreign> ) that similar segments of circles are in the ratio of the squares on
          their bases and that he proved this ( <foreign xml:lang="greek">ἐδείκνυεν</foreign> ) by
          proving ( <foreign xml:lang="greek">ἐκ τοῦ δεῖξαι</foreign> ) that the squares on the
          diameters have the same ratio as the (whole) circles. We know nothing of the method by
          which Hippocrates proved this proposition; but, having regard to the evidence from
          Archimedes quoted above, it is not permissible to suppose that the method was the fully
          developed <hi rend="ital">method of exhaustion</hi> as we know it. </p>
        <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e3871"> （ <hi rend="ital">b</hi> ) As regards the two theorems about the volume of a pyramid and
          of a cone respectively, which Eudoxus was the first to prove, we now have authentic
          evidence in the short treatise by Archimedes discovered by Heiberg in a MS. at
          Constantinople in 1906 and published in <title>Hermes</title> the following year (see now
            <title>Archimedis opera omnia</title> , ed. Heiberg, 2. ed., Vol. II., 1913, pp.
          425-507; T. L. Heath, <title>The Method of Archimedes</title> , Cambridge, 1912). The said
          treatise, complete in all essentials, bears the title <foreign xml:lang="greek"> Ἀρχιμήδους
            περὶ τῶν μηχανικῶν θεωρημάτων πρὸς Ἐρατοσθένην ἔφοδος </foreign> . This
            <quote xml:id="ee-b12-Qd1e3889">Method</quote> (or <quote xml:id="ee-b12-Qd1e3892">Plan of attack</quote> ), addressed to Eratosthenes, is
          none other than the <foreign xml:lang="greek">ἐφόδιον</foreign> on which, according to Suidas,
          Theodosius wrote a commentary, and which is several times cited by Heron in his
            <title>Metrica</title> ; its discovery adds a new and important chapter to the history
          of the integral calculus. In the preface to this work Archimedes alludes to the theorems
          which he first discovered by means of mechanical considerations, but proved afterwards by
          geometry, because the investigation by means of mechanics did not constitute a rigid
          proof; he observes, however, that the mechanical method is of great use for the <hi rend="ital">discovery</hi> of theorems, and it is much easier to provide the rigid proof
          when the fact to be proved has once been discovered than it would be if nothing were known
          to begin with. He goes on: <quote xml:id="ee-b12-Qd1e3904"> Hence too, in the case of those theorems the proof of
            which was first discovered by Eudoxus, namely those relating to the cone and the
            pyramid, that the cone is one third part of the cylinder, and the pyramid one third part
            of the prism, having the same base and equal height, no small part of the credit will
            naturally be assigned to Democritus, who was the first to make the statement (of the
            fact) regarding the said figure [i.e. property], though without proving it. </quote>
          Hence the <hi rend="ital">discovery</hi> of the two theorems must now be attributed to
          Democritus (fl. towards the end of 5th cent. B.C.). The words <quote xml:id="ee-b12-Qd1e3911">without proving
            it</quote> ( <foreign xml:lang="greek">χωρὶς ἀποδείξεως</foreign> ) do not mean that
          Democritus gave no sort of proof, but only that he did not give a proof on the rigorous
          lines required later; for the same words are used by Archimedes of his own investigations
          by means of mechanics, which, however, do constitute a reasoned argument. The character of
          Archimedes' mechanical arguments combined with a passage of Plutarch about a particular
          question in infinitesimals said to have been raised by Democritus may perhaps give a clue
          to the line of Democritus' argument as regards the pyramid. The essential 
          feature of Archimedes' mechanical arguments in this tract is that he regards an area as
          the sum of an infinite number of <hi rend="ital">siraight lines</hi> parallel to one
          another and terminated by the boundary or boundaries of the closed figure the area of
          which is to be found, and a volume as the sum of an infinite number of <hi rend="ital">plane sections</hi> parallel to one another: which is of course the same thing as
          taking (as we do in the integral calculus) the sum of an infinite number of strips of
          breadth <hi rend="ital">dx</hi> (say), when <hi rend="ital">dx</hi> becomes indefinitely
          small, or the sum of an infinite number of parallel laminae of depth <hi rend="ital">dz</hi> (say), when <hi rend="ital">dz</hi> becomes indefinitely small. To give only
          one instance, we may take the case of the area of a segment of a parabola cut off by a
          chord. </p>
        <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e3937"> Let <hi rend="ital">CBA</hi> be the parabolic segment, <hi rend="ital">CE</hi> the
          tangent at <hi rend="ital">C</hi> meeting the <!-- <figure/> --> diameter <hi rend="ital">EBD</hi>
          through the middle point of the chord <hi rend="ital">CA</hi> in <hi rend="ital">E</hi> ,
          so that <hi rend="center">.</hi>
        </p>
        <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e3964"> Draw <hi rend="ital">AF</hi> parallel to <hi rend="ital">ED</hi> meeting <hi rend="ital">CE</hi> produced in <hi rend="ital">F</hi> . Produce <hi rend="ital">CB</hi> to <hi rend="ital">H</hi> so that , where <hi rend="ital">K</hi> is the point in which <hi rend="ital">CH</hi> meets <hi rend="ital">AF</hi> ; and suppose <hi rend="ital">CH</hi>
          to be a lever. </p>
        <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e3998"> Let any diameter <hi rend="ital">MNPO</hi> be drawn meeting the curve in <hi rend="ital">P</hi> and <hi rend="ital">CF</hi> , <hi rend="ital">CK</hi> , <hi rend="ital">CA</hi>
          in <hi rend="ital">M</hi> , <hi rend="ital">N</hi> , <hi rend="ital">O</hi> respectively. </p>
        <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e4026"> Archimedes then observes that <hi rend="center"/> ( <quote xml:id="ee-b12-Qd1e4030">for this is proved in a
            lemma</quote> ), whence <hi rend="center">,</hi> so that, if a straight line <hi rend="ital">TG</hi> equal to <hi rend="ital">PO</hi> be placed with its middle point at
            <hi rend="ital">H</hi> , the straight line <hi rend="ital">MO</hi> with centre of
          gravity at <hi rend="ital">N</hi> , and the straight line <hi rend="ital">TG</hi> with
          centre of gravity at <hi rend="ital">H</hi> , will balance about <hi rend="ital">K</hi> . </p>
        <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e4062"> Taking all other parts of diameters like <hi rend="ital">PO</hi> intercepted between the
          curve and <hi rend="ital">CA</hi> , and placing equal straight lines with their centres of
          gravity at <hi rend="ital">H</hi> , these straight lines collected at <hi rend="ital">H</hi> will balance (about <hi rend="ital">K</hi> ) all the lines like <hi rend="ital">MO</hi> parallel to <hi rend="ital">FA</hi> intercepted within the triangle <hi rend="ital">CFA</hi> in the positions in which they severally lie in the figure. </p>
        <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e4091"> Hence Archimedes infers that an area equal to that of the parabolic segment hung at <hi rend="ital">H</hi> will balance (about <hi rend="ital">K</hi> ) the triangle <hi rend="ital">CFA</hi> hung at its centre of gravity, the point <hi rend="ital">X</hi> (a
          point on <hi rend="ital">CK</hi> such that ), and therefore that <hi rend="center">,</hi>
           from which it follows that <hi rend="center">.</hi>
        </p>
        <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e4116"> The same sort of argument is used for solids, <hi rend="ital">plane sections</hi> taking
          the place of <hi rend="ital">straight lines</hi> . </p>
        <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e4125"> Archimedes is careful to state once more that this method of argument does not
          constitute a <hi rend="ital">proof</hi> . Thus, at the end of the above proposition about
          the parabolic segment, he adds: <quote xml:id="ee-b12-Qd1e4130"> This property is of course not proved by what has
            just been said; but it has furnished a sort of <hi rend="ital">indication</hi> (
              <foreign xml:lang="greek">ἔμφασίν τινα</foreign> ) that the conclusion is true. </quote>
        </p>
        <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e4140"> Let us now turn to the passage of Plutarch ( <title>De Comm. Not. adv. Stoicos</title>
          XXXIX 3) about Democritus above referred to. Plutarch speaks of Democritus as having
          raised the question in natural philosophy ( <foreign xml:lang="greek">φυσικῶς</foreign> ):
            <quote xml:id="ee-b12-Qd1e4148"> if a cone were cut by a plane parallel to the base [by which is clearly meant a
            plane indefinitely near to the base], what must we think of the surfaces of the
            sections, that they are equal or unequal? For, if they are unequal, they will make the
            cone irregular, as having many indentations, like steps, and unevennesses; but, if they
            are equal, the sections will be equal, and the cone will appear to have the property of
            the cylinder and to be made up of equal, not unequal circles, which is very absurd.
          </quote> The phrase <quote xml:id="ee-b12-Qd1e4151">
            <hi rend="ital">made up</hi> of equal...circles </quote> ( <foreign xml:lang="greek">ἐξ ἴσων
            συγκείμενος...κύκλων</foreign> ) shows that Democritus already had the idea of a solid
          being the sum of an infinite number of parallel planes, or indefinitely thin laminae,
          indefinitely near together: a most important anticipation of the same thought which led to
          such fruitful results in Archimedes. If then one may hazard a conjecture as to Democritus'
          argument with regard to a pyramid, it seems probable that he would notice that, if two
          pyramids of the same height and equal triangular bases are respectively cut by planes
          parallel to the base and dividing the heights in the same ratio, the corresponding
          sections of the two pyramids are equal, whence he would infer that the pyramids are equal
          as being the sum of the same infinite number of equal plane sections or indefinitely thin
          laminae. (This would be a particular anticipation of Cavalieri's proposition that the
          areal or solid contents of two figures are equal if two sections of them taken at the same
          height, whatever the height may be, always give equal straight lines or equal surfaces
          respectively.) And Democritus would of course see that the three pyramids into which a
          prism on the same base and of equal height with the original pyramid is divided (as in
          Eucl. <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e4161" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.12.7">XII. 7</ref> ) satisfy this test of equality,
          so that the pyramid would be one third part of the prism. The extension to a pyramid with
          a polygonal base would be easy. And Democritus may have stated the proposition for the
          cone (of course without an absolute proof) as a natural inference from the result of
          increasing indefinitely the number of sides in a regular polygon forming the base of a
          pyramid. 
        </p>
        <div xml:id="ee-b12-Dd1e4165" n="Prop" type="type" org="uniform" sample="complete">
          <head xml:id="ee-b12-Hd1e4167">BOOK XII. PROPOSITIONS.</head>
          <div xml:id="elem.12.1" n="1">
            <head xml:id="ee-b12-Hd1e4172">PROPOSITION 1.</head>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e4175">
              <hi rend="ital"> Similar polygons inscribed in circles are to one another as the
                squares on the diameters. </hi>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e4181"> Let <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> , <hi rend="ital">FGH</hi> be circles, let <hi rend="ital">ABCDE</hi> , <hi rend="ital">FGHKL</hi> be similar polygons inscribed in
              them, and let <hi rend="ital">BM</hi> , <hi rend="ital">GN</hi> be diameters of the
              circles; I say that, as the square on <hi rend="ital">BM</hi> is to the square on <hi rend="ital">GN</hi> , so is the polygon <hi rend="ital">ABCDE</hi> to the polygon
                <hi rend="ital">FGHKL</hi> . <!-- <figure/> -->
            </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e4217"> For let <hi rend="ital">BE</hi> , <hi rend="ital">AM</hi> , <hi rend="ital">GL</hi>
              , <hi rend="ital">FN</hi> be joined. </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e4232"> Now, since the polygon <hi rend="ital">ABCDE</hi> is similar to the polygon <hi rend="ital">FGHKL</hi> , the angle <hi rend="ital">BAE</hi> is equal to the angle
                <hi rend="ital">GFL</hi> , and, as <hi rend="ital">BA</hi> is to <hi rend="ital">AE</hi> , so is <hi rend="ital">GF</hi> to <hi rend="ital">FL</hi> . [VI. Def. I] </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e4261"> Thus <hi rend="ital">BAE</hi> , <hi rend="ital">GFL</hi> are two triangles which
              have one angle equal to one angle, namely the angle <hi rend="ital">BAE</hi> to the
              angle <hi rend="ital">GFL</hi> , and the sides about the equal angles proportional;
              therefore the triangle <hi rend="ital">ABE</hi> is equiangular with the triangle <hi rend="ital">FGL</hi> . [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e4282" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.6.6">VI. 6</ref> ] </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e4286"> Therefore the angle <hi rend="ital">AEB</hi> is equal to the angle <hi rend="ital">FLG</hi> . 
            </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e4295"> But the angle <hi rend="ital">AEB</hi> is equal to the angle <hi rend="ital">AMB</hi> , for they stand on the same circumference; [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e4303" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.3.27">III. 27</ref> ] and the angle <hi rend="ital">FLG</hi> to the angle
                <hi rend="ital">FNG</hi> ; therefore the angle <hi rend="ital">AMB</hi> is also
              equal to the angle <hi rend="ital">FNG</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e4320"> But the right angle <hi rend="ital">BAM</hi> is also equal to the right angle <hi rend="ital">GFN</hi> ; [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e4328" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.3.31">III. 31</ref> ]
              therefore the remaining angle is equal to the remaining angle. [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e4331" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.1.32">I. 32</ref> ] </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e4335"> Therefore the triangle <hi rend="ital">ABM</hi> is equiangular with the triangle <hi rend="ital">FGN</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e4344"> Therefore, proportionally, as <hi rend="ital">BM</hi> is to <hi rend="ital">GN</hi>
              , so is <hi rend="ital">BA</hi> to <hi rend="ital">GF</hi> . [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e4358" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.6.4">VI. 4</ref> ] </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e4363"> But the ratio of the square on <hi rend="ital">BM</hi> to the square on <hi rend="ital">GN</hi> is duplicate of the ratio of <hi rend="ital">BM</hi> to <hi rend="ital">GN</hi> , and the ratio of the polygon <hi rend="ital">ABCDE</hi> to the
              polygon <hi rend="ital">FGHKL</hi> is duplicate of the ratio of <hi rend="ital">BA</hi> to <hi rend="ital">GF</hi> ; [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e4390" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.6.20">VI.
                20</ref> ] therefore also, as the square on <hi rend="ital">BM</hi> is to the square
              on <hi rend="ital">GN</hi> , so is the polygon <hi rend="ital">ABCDE</hi> to the
              polygon <hi rend="ital">FGHKL</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e4407">Therefore etc. Q. E. D.</p>
          </div>
          
          <div xml:id="elem.12.2" n="2">
            <head xml:id="ee-b12-Hd1e4413">PROPOSITION 2.</head>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e4416">
              <hi rend="ital"> Circles are to one another as the squares on the diameters. </hi>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e4422"> Let <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> , <hi rend="ital">EFGH</hi> be circles, and <hi rend="ital">BD</hi> , <hi rend="ital">FH</hi> their diameters; I say that, as the
              circle <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> is to the circle <hi rend="ital">EFGH</hi> , so is
              the square on <hi rend="ital">BD</hi> to the square on <hi rend="ital">FH</hi> .
              <!-- <figure/> -->
            </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e4452"> For, if the square on <hi rend="ital">BD</hi> is not to the square on <hi rend="ital">FH</hi> as the circle <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> is to the circle <hi rend="ital">EFGH</hi> , then, as the square on <hi rend="ital">BD</hi> is to the
              square on <hi rend="ital">FH</hi> , so will the circle <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> be
              either to some less area than the circle <hi rend="ital">EFGH</hi> , or to a greater. </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e4480"> First, let it be in that ratio to a less area <hi rend="ital">S</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e4487"> Let the square <hi rend="ital">EFGH</hi> be inscribed in the circle <hi rend="ital">EFGH</hi> ; then the inscribed square is greater than the half of the circle <hi rend="ital">EFGH</hi> , inasmuch as, if through the points <hi rend="ital">E</hi> ,
                <hi rend="ital">F</hi> , <hi rend="ital">G</hi> , <hi rend="ital">H</hi> we draw
              tangents to the circle, the square <hi rend="ital">EFGH</hi> is half the square
              circumscribed about the circle, and the circle is less than the circumscribed square;
              hence the inscribed square <hi rend="ital">EFGH</hi> is greater than the half of the
              circle <hi rend="ital">EFGH</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e4521"> Let the circumferences <hi rend="ital">EF</hi> , <hi rend="ital">FG</hi> , <hi rend="ital">GH</hi> , <hi rend="ital">HE</hi> be bisected at the points <hi rend="ital">K</hi> , <hi rend="ital">L</hi> , <hi rend="ital">M</hi> , <hi rend="ital">N</hi> , and let <hi rend="ital">EK</hi> , <hi rend="ital">KF</hi> , <hi rend="ital">FL</hi> , <hi rend="ital">LG</hi> , <hi rend="ital">GM</hi> , <hi rend="ital">MH</hi> , <hi rend="ital">HN</hi> , <hi rend="ital">NE</hi> be joined;
              therefore each of the triangles <hi rend="ital">EKF</hi> , <hi rend="ital">FLG</hi> ,
                <hi rend="ital">GMH</hi> , <hi rend="ital">HNE</hi> is also greater than the half of
              the segment of the circle about it, inasmuch as, if through the points <hi rend="ital">K</hi> , <hi rend="ital">L</hi> , <hi rend="ital">M</hi> , <hi rend="ital">N</hi>
              we draw tangents to the circle and complete the parallelograms on the straight lines
                <hi rend="ital">EF</hi> , <hi rend="ital">FG</hi> , <hi rend="ital">GH</hi> , <hi rend="ital">HE</hi> , each of the triangles <hi rend="ital">EKF</hi> , 
              <hi rend="ital">FLG</hi> , <hi rend="ital">GMH</hi> , <hi rend="ital">HNE</hi> will be
              half of the parallelogram about it, while the segment about it is less than the
              parallelogram; hence each of the triangles <hi rend="ital">EKF</hi> , <hi rend="ital">FLG</hi> , <hi rend="ital">GMH</hi> , <hi rend="ital">HNE</hi> is greater than the
              half of the segment of the circle about it. </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e4638"> Thus, by bisecting the remaining circumferences and joining straight lines, and by
              doing this continually, we shall leave some segments of the circle which will be less
              than the excess by which the circle <hi rend="ital">EFGH</hi> exceeds the area <hi rend="ital">S</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e4647"> For it was proved in the first theorem of the tenth book that, if two unequal
              magnitudes be set out, and if from the greater there be subtracted a magnitude greater
              than the half, and from that which is left a greater than the half, and if this be
              done continually, there will be left some magnitude which will be less than the lesser
              magnitude set out. </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e4650"> Let segments be left such as described, and let the segments of the circle <hi rend="ital">EFGH</hi> on <hi rend="ital">EK</hi> , <hi rend="ital">KF</hi> , <hi rend="ital">FL</hi> , <hi rend="ital">LG</hi> , <hi rend="ital">GM</hi> , <hi rend="ital">MH</hi> , <hi rend="ital">HN</hi> , <hi rend="ital">NE</hi> be less than
              the excess by which the circle <hi rend="ital">EFGH</hi> exceeds the area <hi rend="ital">S</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e4687"> Therefore the remainder, the polygon <hi rend="ital">EKFLGMHN</hi> , is greater than
              the area <hi rend="ital">S</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e4697"> Let there be inscribed, also, in the circle <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> the polygon
                <hi rend="ital">AOBPCQDR</hi> similar to the polygon <hi rend="ital">EKFLGMHN</hi> ;
              therefore, as the square on <hi rend="ital">BD</hi> is to the square on <hi rend="ital">FH</hi> , so is the polygon <hi rend="ital">AOBPCQDR</hi> to the polygon
                <hi rend="ital">EKFLGMHN</hi> . [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e4721" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.12.1">XII. 1</ref>
              ] </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e4725"> But, as the square on <hi rend="ital">BD</hi> is to the square on <hi rend="ital">FH</hi> , so also is the circle <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> to the area <hi rend="ital">S</hi> ; therefore also, as the circle <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> is to
              the area <hi rend="ital">S</hi> , so is the polygon <hi rend="ital">AOBPCQDR</hi> to
              the polygon <hi rend="ital">EKFLGMHN</hi> ; [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e4752" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.5.11">V.
                11</ref> ] therefore, alternately, as the circle <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> is to the
              polygon inscribed in it, so is the area <hi rend="ital">S</hi> to the polygon <hi rend="ital">EKFLGMHN</hi> . [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e4765" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.5.16">V. 16</ref> ] </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e4769"> But the circle <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> is greater than the polygon inscribed in
              it; therefore the area <hi rend="ital">S</hi> is also greater than the polygon <hi rend="ital">EKFLGMHN</hi> . 
            </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e4781">But it is also less: which is impossible.</p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e4784"> Therefore, as the square on <hi rend="ital">BD</hi> is to the square on <hi rend="ital">FH</hi> , so is not the circle <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> to any area
              less than the circle <hi rend="ital">EFGH</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e4799"> Similarly we can prove that neither is the circle <hi rend="ital">EFGH</hi> to any
              area less than the circle <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> as the square on <hi rend="ital">FH</hi> is to the square on <hi rend="ital">BD</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e4815"> I say next that neither is the circle <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> to any area greater
              than the circle <hi rend="ital">EFGH</hi> as the square on <hi rend="ital">BD</hi> is
              to the square on <hi rend="ital">FH</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e4830"> For, if possible, let it be in that ratio to a greater area <hi rend="ital">S</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e4836"> Therefore, inversely, as the square on <hi rend="ital">FH</hi> is to the square on
                <hi rend="ital">DB</hi> , so is the area <hi rend="ital">S</hi> to the circle <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e4851"> But, as the area <hi rend="ital">S</hi> is to the circle <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> ,
              so is the circle <hi rend="ital">EFGH</hi> to some area less than the circle <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> ; therefore also, as the square on <hi rend="ital">FH</hi> is
              to the square on <hi rend="ital">BD</hi> , so is the circle <hi rend="ital">EFGH</hi>
              to some area less than the circle <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> : [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e4878" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.5.11">V. 11</ref> ] which was proved impossible. </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e4882"> Therefore, as the square on <hi rend="ital">BD</hi> is to the square on <hi rend="ital">FH</hi> , so is not the circle <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> to any area
              greater than the circle <hi rend="ital">EFGH</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e4897"> And it was proved that neither is it in that ratio to any area less than the circle
                <hi rend="ital">EFGH</hi> ; therefore, as the square on <hi rend="ital">BD</hi> is
              to the square on <hi rend="ital">FH</hi> , so is the circle <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi>
              to the circle <hi rend="ital">EFGH</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e4916">Therefore etc. Q. E. D.</p>
            <div xml:id="elem.12.2.l.1" type="lemma" org="uniform" sample="complete">
              <head xml:id="ee-b12-Hd1e4921">LEMMA.</head>
              <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e4924"> I say that, the area <hi rend="ital">S</hi> being greater than the circle <hi rend="ital">EFGH</hi> , as the area <hi rend="ital">S</hi> is to the circle <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> , so is the circle <hi rend="ital">EFGH</hi> to some area
                less than the circle <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> . </p>
              <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e4946"> For let it be contrived that, as the area <hi rend="ital">S</hi> is to the circle
                  <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> , so is the circle <hi rend="ital">EFGH</hi> to the area
                  <hi rend="ital">T</hi> . </p>
              <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e4961"> I say that the area <hi rend="ital">T</hi> is less than the circle <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> . </p>
              <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e4970"> For since, as the area <hi rend="ital">S</hi> is to the circle <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> , so is the circle <hi rend="ital">EFGH</hi> to the area <hi rend="ital">T</hi> ,  therefore, alternately, as the area <hi rend="ital">S</hi> is to the circle <hi rend="ital">EFGH</hi> , so is the circle
                  <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> to the area <hi rend="ital">T</hi> . [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e4997" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.5.16">V. 16</ref> ] </p>
              <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e5002"> But the area <hi rend="ital">S</hi> is greater than the circle <hi rend="ital">EFGH</hi> ; therefore the circle <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> is also greater than
                the area <hi rend="ital">T</hi> . </p>
              <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e5017"> Hence, as the area <hi rend="ital">S</hi> is to the circle <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> , so is the circle <hi rend="ital">EFGH</hi> to some area less than the
                circle <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> . Q. E. D. </p>
            </div>
          </div>
          <div xml:id="elem.12.3" n="3">
            <head xml:id="ee-b12-Hd1e5036">PROPOSITION 3.</head>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e5039">
              <hi rend="ital"> Any pyramid which has a triangular base is divided into two pyramids
                equal and similar to one another </hi> , <hi rend="ital">similar to the whole and
                having triangular bases</hi> , <hi rend="ital"> and into two equal prisms; and the
                two prisms are greater than the half of the whole pyramid. </hi>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e5051"> Let there be a pyramid of which the triangle <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> is the base
              and the point <hi rend="ital">D</hi> the vertex; I say that the pyramid <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> is divided into two pyramids equal to one another, having
              triangular bases and similar to the whole pyramid, and into two equal prisms; and the
              two prisms are greater than the half of the whole pyramid. <!-- <figure/> -->
            </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e5065"> For let <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> , <hi rend="ital">BC</hi> , <hi rend="ital">CA</hi>
              , <hi rend="ital">AD</hi> , <hi rend="ital">DB</hi> , <hi rend="ital">DC</hi> be
              bisected at the points <hi rend="ital">E</hi> , <hi rend="ital">F</hi> , <hi rend="ital">G</hi> , <hi rend="ital">H</hi> , <hi rend="ital">K</hi> , <hi rend="ital">L</hi> , and let <hi rend="ital">HE</hi> , <hi rend="ital">EG</hi> , <hi rend="ital">GH</hi> , <hi rend="ital">HK</hi> , <hi rend="ital">KL</hi> , <hi rend="ital">LH</hi> , <hi rend="ital">KF</hi> , <hi rend="ital">FG</hi> be joined. </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e5131"> Since <hi rend="ital">AE</hi> is equal to <hi rend="ital">EB</hi> , and <hi rend="ital">AH</hi> to <hi rend="ital">DH</hi> , therefore <hi rend="ital">EH</hi>
              is parallel to <hi rend="ital">DB</hi> . [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e5152" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.6.2">VI.
                2</ref> ] 
            </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e5157"> For the same reason <hi rend="ital">HK</hi> is also parallel to <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e5166"> Therefore <hi rend="ital">HEBK</hi> is a parallelogram; therefore <hi rend="ital">HK</hi> is equal to <hi rend="ital">EB</hi> . [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e5177" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.1.34">I. 34</ref> ] </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e5181"> But <hi rend="ital">EB</hi> is equal to <hi rend="ital">EA</hi> ; therefore <hi rend="ital">AE</hi> is also equal to <hi rend="ital">HK</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e5196"> But <hi rend="ital">AH</hi> is also equal to <hi rend="ital">HD</hi> ; therefore the
              two sides <hi rend="ital">EA</hi> , <hi rend="ital">AH</hi> are equal to the two sides
                <hi rend="ital">KH</hi> , <hi rend="ital">HD</hi> respectively, and the angle <hi rend="ital">EAH</hi> is equal to the angle <hi rend="ital">KHD</hi> ; therefore the
              base <hi rend="ital">EH</hi> is equal to the base <hi rend="ital">KD</hi> . [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e5229" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.1.4">I. 4</ref> ] </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e5233"> Therefore the triangle <hi rend="ital">AEH</hi> is equal and similar to the triangle
                <hi rend="ital">HKD</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e5242"> For the same reason the triangle <hi rend="ital">AHG</hi> is also equal and similar
              to the triangle <hi rend="ital">HLD</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e5252"> Now, since two straight lines <hi rend="ital">EH</hi> , <hi rend="ital">HG</hi>
              meeting one another are parallel to two straight lines <hi rend="ital">KD</hi> , <hi rend="ital">DL</hi> meeting one another, and are not in the same plane, they will
              contain equal angles. [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e5266" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.11.10">XI. 10</ref> ] </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e5270"> Therefore the angle <hi rend="ital">EHG</hi> is equal to the angle <hi rend="ital">KDL</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e5279"> And, since the two straight lines <hi rend="ital">EH</hi> , <hi rend="ital">HG</hi>
              are equal to the two <hi rend="ital">KD</hi> , <hi rend="ital">DL</hi> respectively,
              and the angle <hi rend="ital">EHG</hi> is equal to the angle <hi rend="ital">KDL</hi>
              , therefore the base <hi rend="ital">EG</hi> is equal to the base <hi rend="ital">KL</hi> ; [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e5306" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.1.4">I. 4</ref> ] therefore the
              triangle <hi rend="ital">EHG</hi> is equal and similar to the triangle <hi rend="ital">KDL</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e5316"> For the same reason the triangle <hi rend="ital">AEG</hi> is also equal and similar
              to the triangle <hi rend="ital">HKL</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e5325"> Therefore the pyramid of which the triangle <hi rend="ital">AEG</hi> is the base and
              the point <hi rend="ital">H</hi> the vertex is equal and similar to the pyramid of
              which the triangle <hi rend="ital">HKL</hi> is the base and the point <hi rend="ital">D</hi> the vertex. [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e5339" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.11.def.10">XI. Def. 10</ref> ] </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e5343"> And, since <hi rend="ital">HK</hi> has been drawn parallel to <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> , one of the sides of the triangle <hi rend="ital">ADB</hi> , 
              the triangle <hi rend="ital">ADB</hi> is equiangular to the triangle <hi rend="ital">DHK</hi> , [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e5361" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.1.29">I. 29</ref> ] and they have
              their sides proportional; therefore the triangle <hi rend="ital">ADB</hi> is similar
              to the triangle <hi rend="ital">DHK</hi> . [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e5370" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.6.def.1">VI. Def. 1</ref> ] </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e5375"> For the same reason the triangle <hi rend="ital">DBC</hi> is also similar to the
              triangle <hi rend="ital">DKL</hi> , and the triangle <hi rend="ital">ADC</hi> to the
              triangle <hi rend="ital">DLH</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e5390"> Now, since the two straight lines <hi rend="ital">BA</hi> , <hi rend="ital">AC</hi>
              meeting one another are parallel to the two straight lines <hi rend="ital">KH</hi> ,
                <hi rend="ital">HL</hi> meeting one another, not in the same plane, they will
              contain equal angles. [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e5404" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.11.10">XI. 10</ref> ] </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e5408"> Therefore the angle <hi rend="ital">BAC</hi> is equal to the angle <hi rend="ital">KHL</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e5417"> And, as <hi rend="ital">BA</hi> is to <hi rend="ital">AC</hi> , so is <hi rend="ital">KH</hi> to <hi rend="ital">HL</hi> ; therefore the triangle <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> is similar to the triangle <hi rend="ital">HKL</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e5439"> Therefore also the pyramid of which the triangle <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> is the
              base and the point <hi rend="ital">D</hi> the vertex is similar to the pyramid of
              which the triangle <hi rend="ital">HKL</hi> is the base and the point <hi rend="ital">D</hi> the vertex. </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e5454"> But the pyramid of which the triangle <hi rend="ital">HKL</hi> is the base and the
              point <hi rend="ital">D</hi> the vertex was proved similar to the pyramid of which the
              triangle <hi rend="ital">AEG</hi> is the base and the point <hi rend="ital">H</hi> the
              vertex. </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e5470"> Therefore each of the pyramids <hi rend="ital">AEGH</hi> , <hi rend="ital">HKLD</hi>
              is similar to the whole pyramid <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e5482"> Next, since <hi rend="ital">BF</hi> is equal to <hi rend="ital">FC</hi> , the
              parallelogram <hi rend="ital">EBFG</hi> is double of the triangle <hi rend="ital">GFC</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e5497"> And since, if there be two prisms of equal height, and one have a parallelogram as
              base, and the other a triangle, and if the parallelogram be double of the triangle,
              the prisms are equal, [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e5499" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.11.39">XI. 39</ref> ]
              therefore the prism contained by the two triangles <hi rend="ital">BKF</hi> , <hi rend="ital">EHG</hi> , and the three parallelograms <hi rend="ital">EBFG</hi> , <hi rend="ital">EBKH</hi> , <hi rend="ital">HKFG</hi> is equal to the prism contained by
              the two triangles <hi rend="ital">GFC</hi> , <hi rend="ital">HKL</hi> and the three
              parallelograms <hi rend="ital">KFCL</hi> , <hi rend="ital">LCGH</hi> , <hi rend="ital">HKFG</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e5534"> And it is manifest that each of the prisms, namely that in which the parallelogram
                <hi rend="ital">EBFG</hi> is the base and the straight line <hi rend="ital">HK</hi>
              is its opposite, and that in which the triangle <hi rend="ital">GFC</hi> is the base
              and the triangle <hi rend="ital">HKL</hi> its opposite, is greater than each of the
              pyramids of which the triangles <hi rend="ital">AEG</hi> , <hi rend="ital">HKL</hi>
              are the bases and the points <hi rend="ital">H</hi> , <hi rend="ital">D</hi> the
              vertices,  inasmuch as, if we join the straight lines <hi rend="ital">EF</hi> , <hi rend="ital">EK</hi> , the prism in which the parallelogram <hi rend="ital">EBFG</hi> is the base and the straight line <hi rend="ital">HK</hi> its
              opposite is greater than the pyramid of which the triangle <hi rend="ital">EBF</hi> is
              the base and the point <hi rend="ital">K</hi> the vertex. </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e5581"> But the pyramid of which the triangle <hi rend="ital">EBF</hi> is the base and the
              point <hi rend="ital">K</hi> the vertex is equal to the pyramid of which the triangle
                <hi rend="ital">AEG</hi> is the base and the point <hi rend="ital">H</hi> the
              vertex; for they are contained by equal and similar planes. </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e5596"> Hence also the prism in which the parallelogram <hi rend="ital">EBFG</hi> is the
              base and the straight line <hi rend="ital">HK</hi> its opposite is greater than the
              pyramid of which the triangle <hi rend="ital">AEG</hi> is the base and the point <hi rend="ital">H</hi> the vertex. </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e5612"> But the prism in which the parallelogram <hi rend="ital">EBFG</hi> is the base and
              the straight line <hi rend="ital">HK</hi> its opposite is equal to the prism in which
              the triangle <hi rend="ital">GFC</hi> is the base and the triangle <hi rend="ital">HKL</hi> its opposite, and the pyramid of which the triangle <hi rend="ital">AEG</hi> is the base and the point <hi rend="ital">H</hi> the vertex is equal to
              the pyramid of which the triangle <hi rend="ital">HKL</hi> is the base and the point
                <hi rend="ital">D</hi> the vertex. </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e5640"> Therefore the said two prisms are greater than the said two pyramids of which the
              triangles <hi rend="ital">AEG</hi> , <hi rend="ital">HKL</hi> are the bases and the
              points <hi rend="ital">H</hi> , <hi rend="ital">D</hi> the vertices. </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e5655"> Therefore the whole pyramid, of which the triangle <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> is the
              base and the point <hi rend="ital">D</hi> the vertex, has been divided into two
              pyramids equal to one another and into two equal prisms, and the two prisms are
              greater than the half of the whole pyramid. Q. E. D. </p>
          </div>
          <div xml:id="elem.12.4" n="4">
            <head xml:id="ee-b12-Hd1e5667">PROPOSITION 4.</head>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e5670">
              <hi rend="ital"> If there be two pyramids of the same height which have triangular
                bases </hi> , <hi rend="ital"> and cach of them be divided into two pyramids equal
                to one another and similar to the whole, and into two equal prisms </hi> , <hi rend="ital">then</hi> , <hi rend="ital"> as the base of the one pyramid is to the
                base of the other pyramid </hi> , <hi rend="ital"> so will all the prisms in the one
                pyramid be to all the prisms </hi> , <hi rend="ital">being equal in multitude</hi> ,
                <hi rend="ital">in the other pyramid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e5695"> Let there be two pyramids of the same height which have the triangular bases <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> , <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi> , and vertices the points <hi rend="ital">G</hi> , <hi rend="ital">H</hi> , and let each of them be divided into
              two pyramids equal to one another and similar to the whole and into two equal prisms;
              [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e5709" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.12.3">XII. 3</ref> ] I say that, as the base <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> is to the base <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi> , so are all the prisms
              in the pyramid <hi rend="ital">ABCG</hi> to all the prisms, being equal in multitude,
              in the pyramid <hi rend="ital">DEFH</hi> , 
            </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e5726"> For, since <hi rend="ital">BO</hi> is equal to <hi rend="ital">OC</hi> , and <hi rend="ital">AL</hi> to <hi rend="ital">LC</hi> , therefore <hi rend="ital">LO</hi>
              is parallel to <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> , and the triangle <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> is
              similar to the triangle <hi rend="ital">LOC</hi> . <!-- <figure/> -->
            </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e5756"> For the same reason the triangle <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi> is also similar to the
              triangle <hi rend="ital">RVF</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e5766"> And, since <hi rend="ital">BC</hi> is double of <hi rend="ital">CO</hi> , and <hi rend="ital">EF</hi> of <hi rend="ital">FV</hi> , therefore, as <hi rend="ital">BC</hi> is to <hi rend="ital">CO</hi> , so is <hi rend="ital">EF</hi> to <hi rend="ital">FV</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e5794"> And on <hi rend="ital">BC</hi> , <hi rend="ital">CO</hi> are described the similar
              and similarly situated rectilineal figures <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> , <hi rend="ital">LOC</hi> , and on <hi rend="ital">EF</hi> , <hi rend="ital">FV</hi> the similar and
              similarly situated figures <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi> , <hi rend="ital">RVF</hi> ;
              therefore, as the triangle <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> is to the triangle <hi rend="ital">LOC</hi> , so is the triangle <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi> to the triangle <hi rend="ital">RVF</hi> ; [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e5834" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.6.22">VI. 22</ref> ]
              therefore, alternately, as the triangle <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> is to the triangle
                <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi> , so is the triangle <hi rend="ital">LOC</hi> to the
              triangle <hi rend="ital">RVF</hi> . [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e5850" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.5.16">V.
                16</ref> ] </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e5854"> But, as the triangle <hi rend="ital">LOC</hi> is to the triangle <hi rend="ital">RVF</hi> , so is the prism in which the triangle <hi rend="ital">LOC</hi> is the
              base and <hi rend="ital">PMN</hi> its opposite to the prism in which the triangle <hi rend="ital">RVF</hi> is the base and <hi rend="ital">STU</hi> its opposite; [Lemma
              following] therefore also, as the triangle <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> is to the triangle
                <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi> , so is the prism in which the triangle <hi rend="ital">LOC</hi> is the base and <hi rend="ital">PMN</hi> its opposite to the prism in
              which the triangle <hi rend="ital">RVF</hi> is the base and <hi rend="ital">STU</hi>
              its opposite. </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e5895"> But, as the said prisms are to one another, so is the prism in which the
              parallelogram <hi rend="ital">KBOL</hi> is the base and the straight line <hi rend="ital">PM</hi> its opposite to the prism in which the parallelogram <hi rend="ital">QEVR</hi> is the base and the straight line <hi rend="ital">ST</hi> its
              opposite. [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e5909" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.11.39">XI. 39</ref> ; cf. <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e5913" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.12.3">XII. 3</ref> ] 
            </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e5917"> Therefore also the two prisms, that in which the parallelogram <hi rend="ital">KBOL</hi> is the base and <hi rend="ital">PM</hi> its opposite, and that in which
              the triangle <hi rend="ital">LOC</hi> is the base and <hi rend="ital">PMN</hi> its
              opposite, are to the prisms in which <hi rend="ital">QEVR</hi> is the base and the
              straight line <hi rend="ital">ST</hi> its opposite and in which the triangle <hi rend="ital">RVF</hi> is the base and <hi rend="ital">STU</hi> its opposite in the
              same ratio [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e5944" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.5.12">V. 12</ref> ] </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e5948"> Therefore also, as the base <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> is to the base <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi> , so are the said two prisms to the said two prisms. </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e5958"> And similarly, if the pyramids <hi rend="ital">PMNG</hi> , <hi rend="ital">STUH</hi>
              be divided into two prisms and two pyramids, as the base <hi rend="ital">PMN</hi> is
              to the base <hi rend="ital">STU</hi> , so will the two prisms in the pyramid <hi rend="ital">PMNG</hi> be to the two prisms in the pyramid <hi rend="ital">STUH</hi>
              . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e5980"> But, as the base <hi rend="ital">PMN</hi> is to the base <hi rend="ital">STU</hi> ,
              so is the base <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> to the base <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi> ; for the
              triangles <hi rend="ital">PMN</hi> , <hi rend="ital">STU</hi> are equal to the
              triangles <hi rend="ital">LOC</hi> , <hi rend="ital">RVF</hi> respectively. </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e6008"> Therefore also, as the base <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> is to the base <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi> , so are the four prisms to the four prisms. </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e6017"> And similarly also, if we divide the remaining pyramids into two pyramids and into
              two prisms, then, as the base <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> is to the base <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi> , so will all the prisms in the pyramid <hi rend="ital">ABCG</hi> be to
              all the prisms, being equal in multitude, in the pyramid <hi rend="ital">DEFH</hi> .
              Q. E. D. </p>
            <div xml:id="elem.12.4.l.1" type="lemma" org="uniform" sample="complete">
              <head xml:id="ee-b12-Hd1e6034">LEMMA.</head>
              <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e6037"> But that, as the triangle <hi rend="ital">LOC</hi> is to the triangle <hi rend="ital">RVF</hi> , so is the prism in which the triangle <hi rend="ital">LOC</hi> is the base and <hi rend="ital">PMN</hi> its opposite to the prism in
                which the triangle <hi rend="ital">RVF</hi> is the base and <hi rend="ital">STU</hi>
                its opposite, we must prove as follows. </p>
              <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e6059"> For in the same figure let perpendiculars be conceived drawn from <hi rend="ital">G</hi> , <hi rend="ital">H</hi> to the planes <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> , <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi> ; these are of course equal because, by hypothesis, the
                pyramids are of equal height. </p>
              <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e6074"> Now, since the two straight lines <hi rend="ital">GC</hi> and the perpendicular
                from <hi rend="ital">G</hi> are cut by the parallel planes <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi>
                , <hi rend="ital">PMN</hi> , they will be cut in the same ratios. [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e6088" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.11.17">XI. 17</ref> ] 
              </p>
              <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e6092"> And <hi rend="ital">GC</hi> is bisected by the plane <hi rend="ital">PMN</hi> at
                  <hi rend="ital">N</hi> ; therefore the perpendicular from <hi rend="ital">G</hi>
                to the plane <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> will also be bisected by the plane <hi rend="ital">PMN</hi> . </p>
              <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e6115"> For the same reason the perpendicular from <hi rend="ital">H</hi> to the plane <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi> will also be bisected by the plane <hi rend="ital">STU</hi> . </p>
              <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e6127"> And the perpendiculars from <hi rend="ital">G</hi> , <hi rend="ital">H</hi> to the
                planes <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> , <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi> are equal; therefore the
                perpendiculars from the triangles <hi rend="ital">PMN</hi> , <hi rend="ital">STU</hi> to the planes <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> , <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi> are
                also equal. </p>
              <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e6155"> Therefore the prisms in which the triangles <hi rend="ital">LOC</hi> , <hi rend="ital">RVF</hi> are bases, and <hi rend="ital">PMN</hi> , <hi rend="ital">STU</hi> their opposites, are of equal height. </p>
              <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e6170"> Hence also the parallelepipedal solids described from the said prisms are of equal
                height and are to one another as their bases; [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e6172" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.11.32">XI. 32</ref> ] therefore their halves, namely the said prisms, are
                to one another as the base <hi rend="ital">LOC</hi> is to the base <hi rend="ital">RVF</hi> . Q. E. D. </p>
            </div>
          </div>
          <div xml:id="elem.12.5" n="5">
            <head xml:id="ee-b12-Hd1e6187">PROPOSITION 5.</head>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e6190">
              <hi rend="ital"> Pyramids which are of the same height and have triangular bases are
                to one another as the bases. </hi>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e6196"> Let there be pyramids of the same height, of which the triangles <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> , <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi> are the bases and the points <hi rend="ital">G</hi> , <hi rend="ital">H</hi> the vertices; I say that, as the base <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> is to the base <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi> , so is the pyramid <hi rend="ital">ABCG</hi> to the pyramid <hi rend="ital">DEFH</hi> . <!-- <figure/> -->
            </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e6226"> For, if the pyramid <hi rend="ital">ABCG</hi> is not to the pyramid <hi rend="ital">DEFH</hi> as the base <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> is to the base <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi> , then, as the base <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> is to the base <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi> , so will the pyramid <hi rend="ital">ABCG</hi> be either to
              some solid less than the pyramid <hi rend="ital">DEFH</hi> or to a greater. </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e6254"> Let it, first, be in that ratio to a less solid <hi rend="ital">W</hi> , and let the
              pyramid <hi rend="ital">DEFH</hi> be divided into two pyramids equal to one another
              and similar to the whole and into two equal prisms; then the two prisms are greater
              than the half of the whole pyramid. [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e6262" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.12.3">XII.
                3</ref> ] 
            </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e6267"> Again, let the pyramids arising from the division be similarly divided, and let this
              be done continually until there are left over from the pyramid <hi rend="ital">DEFH</hi> some pyramids which are less than the excess by which the pyramid <hi rend="ital">DEFH</hi> exceeds the solid <hi rend="ital">W</hi> . [X. I] </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e6279"> Let such be left, and let them be, for the sake of argument, <hi rend="ital">DQRS</hi> , <hi rend="ital">STUH</hi> ; therefore the remainders, the prisms in the
              pyramid <hi rend="ital">DEFH</hi> , are greater than the solid <hi rend="ital">W</hi>
              . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e6294"> Let the pyramid <hi rend="ital">ABCG</hi> also be divided similarly, and a similar
              number of times, with the pyramid <hi rend="ital">DEFH</hi> ; therefore, as the base
                <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> is to the base <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi> , so are the prisms
              in the pyramid <hi rend="ital">ABCG</hi> to the prisms in the pyramid <hi rend="ital">DEFH</hi> . [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e6315" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.12.4">XII. 4</ref> ] </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e6319"> But, as the base <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> is to the base <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi> ,
              so also is the pyramid <hi rend="ital">ABCG</hi> to the solid <hi rend="ital">W</hi> ;
              therefore also, as the pyramid <hi rend="ital">ABCG</hi> is to the solid <hi rend="ital">W</hi> , so are the prisms in the pyramid <hi rend="ital">ABCG</hi> to
              the prisms in the pyramid <hi rend="ital">DEFH</hi> ; [V. II] therefore, alternately,
              as the pyramid <hi rend="ital">ABCG</hi> is to the prisms in it, so is the solid <hi rend="ital">W</hi> to the prisms in the pyramid <hi rend="ital">DEFH</hi> . [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e6356" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.5.16">V. 16</ref> ] </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e6360"> But the pyramid <hi rend="ital">ABCG</hi> is greater than the prisms in it;
              therefore the solid <hi rend="ital">W</hi> is also greater than the prisms in the
              pyramid <hi rend="ital">DEFH</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e6372">But it is also less: which is impossible.</p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e6376"> Therefore the prism <hi rend="ital">ABCG</hi> is not to any solid less than the
              pyramid <hi rend="ital">DEFH</hi> as the base <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> is to the base
                <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e6391"> Similarly it can be proved that neither is the pyramid <hi rend="ital">DEFH</hi> to
              any solid less than the pyramid <hi rend="ital">ABCG</hi> as the base <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi> is to the base <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e6406"> I say next that neither is the pyramid <hi rend="ital">ABCG</hi> to any solid
              greater than the pyramid <hi rend="ital">DEFH</hi> as the base <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> is to the base <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e6421"> For, if possible, let it be in that ratio to a greater solid <hi rend="ital">W</hi>
              ; therefore, inversely, as the base <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi> is to the base <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> , so is the solid <hi rend="ital">W</hi> to the pyramid <hi rend="ital">ABCG</hi> . 
            </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e6439"> But, as the solid <hi rend="ital">W</hi> is to the solid <hi rend="ital">ABCG</hi> ,
              so is the pyramid <hi rend="ital">DEFH</hi> to some solid less than the pyramid <hi rend="ital">ABCG</hi> , as was before proved; [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e6453" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.12.2.l.1">XII. 2, Lemma</ref> ] therefore also, as the base <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi> is to the base <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> , so is the pyramid <hi rend="ital">DEFH</hi> to some solid less than the pyramid <hi rend="ital">ABCG</hi>
              : [V. II] which was proved absurd. </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e6470"> Therefore the pyramid <hi rend="ital">ABCG</hi> is not to any solid greater than the
              pyramid <hi rend="ital">DEFH</hi> as the base <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> is to the base
                <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e6486"> But it was proved that neither is it in that ratio to a less solid. </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e6489"> Therefore, as the base <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> is to the base <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi> , so is the pyramid <hi rend="ital">ABCG</hi> to the pyramid <hi rend="ital">DEFH</hi> . Q. E. D. </p>
          </div>
          
          <div xml:id="elem.12.6" n="6">
            <head xml:id="ee-b12-Hd1e6507">PROPOSITION 6.</head>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e6510">
              <hi rend="ital"> Pyramids which are of the same height and have polygonal bases are to
                one another as the bases. </hi>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e6516"> Let there be pyramids of the same height of which the polygons <hi rend="ital">ABCDE</hi> , <hi rend="ital">FGHKL</hi> are the bases and the points <hi rend="ital">M</hi> , <hi rend="ital">N</hi> the vertices; I say that, as the base
                <hi rend="ital">ABCDE</hi> is to the base <hi rend="ital">FGHKL</hi> , so is the
              pyramid <hi rend="ital">ABCDEM</hi> to the pyramid <hi rend="ital">FGHKLN</hi> .
              <!-- <figure/> -->
            </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e6546"> For let <hi rend="ital">AC</hi> , <hi rend="ital">AD</hi> , <hi rend="ital">FH</hi>
              , <hi rend="ital">FK</hi> be joined. </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e6561"> Since then <hi rend="ital">ABCM</hi> , <hi rend="ital">ACDM</hi> are two pyramids
              which have triangular bases and equal height, they are to one another as the bases; [
                <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e6569" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.12.5">XII. 5</ref> ] therefore, as the base <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> is to the base <hi rend="ital">ACD</hi> , so is the pyramid <hi rend="ital">ABCM</hi> to the pyramid <hi rend="ital">ACDM</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e6587"> And, <foreign xml:lang="la">componendo</foreign> , as the base <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi>
              is to the base <hi rend="ital">ACD</hi> , so is the pyramid <hi rend="ital">ABCDM</hi>
              to the pyramid <hi rend="ital">ACDM</hi> . [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e6605" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.5.18">V.
                18</ref> ] </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e6609"> But also, as the base <hi rend="ital">ACD</hi> is to the base <hi rend="ital">ADE</hi> , so is the pyramid <hi rend="ital">ACDM</hi> to the pyramid <hi rend="ital">ADEM</hi> . [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e6623" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.12.5">XII. 5</ref> ] </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e6627"> Therefore, <foreign xml:lang="la">ex aequali</foreign> , as the base <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> is to the base <hi rend="ital">ADE</hi> , so is the pyramid <hi rend="ital">ABCDM</hi> to the pyramid <hi rend="ital">ADEM</hi> . [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e6645" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.5.22">V. 22</ref> ] </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e6649"> And again <foreign xml:lang="la">componendo</foreign> , as the base <hi rend="ital">ABCDE</hi> is to the base <hi rend="ital">ADE</hi> , so is the pyramid <hi rend="ital">ABCDEM</hi> to the pyramid <hi rend="ital">ADEM</hi> . [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e6667" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.5.18">V. 18</ref> ] </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e6671"> Similarly also it can be proved that, as the base <hi rend="ital">FGHKL</hi> is to
              the base <hi rend="ital">FGH</hi> , so is the pyramid <hi rend="ital">FGHKLN</hi> to
              the pyramid <hi rend="ital">FGHN</hi> . 
            </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e6686"> And, since <hi rend="ital">ADEM</hi> , <hi rend="ital">FGHN</hi> are two pyramids
              which have triangular bases and equal height, therefore, as the base <hi rend="ital">ADE</hi> is to the base <hi rend="ital">FGH</hi> , so is the pyramid <hi rend="ital">ADEM</hi> to the pyramid <hi rend="ital">FGHN</hi> . [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e6707" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.12.5">XII. 5</ref> ] </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e6712"> But, as the base <hi rend="ital">ADE</hi> is to the base <hi rend="ital">ABCDE</hi>
              , so was the pyramid <hi rend="ital">ADEM</hi> to the pyramid <hi rend="ital">ABCDEM</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e6727"> Therefore also, <foreign xml:lang="la">ex aequali</foreign> , as the base <hi rend="ital">ABCDE</hi> is to the base <hi rend="ital">FGH</hi> , so is the pyramid
                <hi rend="ital">ABCDEM</hi> to the pyramid <hi rend="ital">FGHN</hi> . [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e6745" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.5.22">V. 22</ref> ] </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e6749"> But further, as the base <hi rend="ital">FGH</hi> is to the base <hi rend="ital">FGHKL</hi> , so also was the pyramid <hi rend="ital">FGHN</hi> to the pyramid <hi rend="ital">FGHKLN</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e6764"> Therefore also, <hi rend="ital">ex aequali</hi> , as the base <hi rend="ital">ABCDE</hi> is to the base <hi rend="ital">FGHKL</hi> , so is the pyramid <hi rend="ital">ABCDEM</hi> to the pyramid <hi rend="ital">FGHKLN</hi> . [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e6782" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.5.22">V. 22</ref> ] Q. E. D. </p>
          </div>
          
          <div xml:id="elem.12.7" n="7">
            <head xml:id="ee-b12-Hd1e6789">PROPOSITION 7.</head>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e6792">
              <hi rend="ital"> Any prism which has a triangular base is divided into three pyramids
                equal to one another which have triangular bases. </hi>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e6798"> Let there be a prism in which the triangle <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> is the base and
                <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi> its opposite; I say that the prism <hi rend="ital">ABCDEF</hi> is divided into three pyramids equal to one another, which have
              triangular bases. <!-- <figure/> -->
            </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e6812"> For let <hi rend="ital">BD</hi> , <hi rend="ital">EC</hi> , <hi rend="ital">CD</hi>
              be joined. </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e6824"> Since <hi rend="ital">ABED</hi> is a parallelogram, and <hi rend="ital">BD</hi> is
              its diameter, therefore the triangle <hi rend="ital">ABD</hi> is equal to the triangle
                <hi rend="ital">EBD</hi> ; [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e6838" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.1.34">I. 34</ref> ]
              therefore also the pyramid of which the triangle <hi rend="ital">ABD</hi> is the base
              and the point <hi rend="ital">C</hi> the vertex is equal to the pyramid of which the
              triangle <hi rend="ital">DEB</hi> is the base and the point <hi rend="ital">C</hi> the
              vertex. [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e6854" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.12.5">XII. 5</ref> ] </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e6859"> But the pyramid of which the triangle <hi rend="ital">DEB</hi> is the base and the
              point <hi rend="ital">C</hi> the vertex is the same with the pyramid of which the
              triangle <hi rend="ital">EBC</hi> is the base and the point <hi rend="ital">D</hi> the
              vertex; for they are contained by the same planes. </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e6874"> Therefore the pyramid of which the triangle <hi rend="ital">ABD</hi> is the base and
              the point <hi rend="ital">C</hi> the vertex is also equal to the pyramid of which the
              triangle <hi rend="ital">EBC</hi> is the base and the point <hi rend="ital">D</hi> the
              vertex. </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e6889"> Again, since <hi rend="ital">FCBE</hi> is a parallelogram, and <hi rend="ital">CE</hi> is its diameter, the triangle <hi rend="ital">CEF</hi> is equal to the
              triangle <hi rend="ital">CBE</hi> . [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e6903" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.1.34">I.
                34</ref> ] </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e6907"> Therefore also the pyramid of which the triangle <hi rend="ital">BCE</hi> is the
              base and the point <hi rend="ital">D</hi> the vertex is equal to the pyramid of which
              the triangle <hi rend="ital">ECF</hi> is the base and the point <hi rend="ital">D</hi>
              the vertex. [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e6921" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.12.5">XII. 5</ref> ] </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e6925"> But the pyramid of which the triangle <hi rend="ital">BCE</hi> is the base and the
              point <hi rend="ital">D</hi> the vertex was proved equal to the pyramid of which the
              triangle <hi rend="ital">ABD</hi> is the base and the point <hi rend="ital">C</hi> the
              vertex;  therefore also the pyramid of which the triangle <hi rend="ital">CEF</hi> is the base and the point <hi rend="ital">D</hi> the vertex is equal to
              the pyramid of which the triangle <hi rend="ital">ABD</hi> is the base and the point
                <hi rend="ital">C</hi> the vertex; therefore the prism <hi rend="ital">ABCDEF</hi>
              has been divided into three pyramids equal to one another which have triangular bases. </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e6956"> And, since the pyramid of which the triangle <hi rend="ital">ABD</hi> is the base
              and the point <hi rend="ital">C</hi> the vertex is the same with the pyramid of which
              the triangle <hi rend="ital">CAB</hi> is the base and the point <hi rend="ital">D</hi>
              the vertex, for they are contained by the same planes, while the pyramid of which the
              triangle <hi rend="ital">ABD</hi> is the base and the point <hi rend="ital">C</hi> the
              vertex was proved to be a third of the prism in which the triangle <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> is the base and <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi> its opposite, therefore also the
              pyramid of which the triangle <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> is the base and the point <hi rend="ital">D</hi> the vertex is a third of the prism which has the same base, the
              triangle <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> , and <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi> as its opposite. </p>
            <div xml:id="elem.12.7.p.1" type="porism" org="uniform" sample="complete">
              <head xml:id="ee-b12-Hd1e7000">PORISM.</head>
              <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e7003"> From this it is manifest that any pyramid is a third part of the prism which has
                the same base with it and equal height. Q. E. D. </p>
            </div>
          </div>
          <div xml:id="elem.12.8" n="8">
            <head xml:id="ee-b12-Hd1e7010">PROPOSITION 8.</head>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e7013">
              <hi rend="ital"> Similar pyramids which have triangular bases are in the triplicate
                ratio of their corresponding sides. </hi>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e7019"> Let there be similar and similarly situated pyramids of  which the
              triangles <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> , <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi> , are the bases and the
              points <hi rend="ital">G</hi> , <hi rend="ital">H</hi> the vertices; I say that the
              pyramid <hi rend="ital">ABCG</hi> has to the pyramid <hi rend="ital">DEFH</hi> the
              ratio triplicate of that which <hi rend="ital">BC</hi> has to <hi rend="ital">EF</hi>
              . <!-- <figure/> -->
            </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e7049"> For let the parallelepipedal solids <hi rend="ital">BGML</hi> , <hi rend="ital">EHQP</hi> be completed. </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e7058"> Now, since the pyramid <hi rend="ital">ABCG</hi> is similar to the pyramid <hi rend="ital">DEFH</hi> , therefore the angle <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> is equal to the
              angle <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi> , the angle <hi rend="ital">GBC</hi> to the angle <hi rend="ital">HEF</hi> , and the angle <hi rend="ital">ABG</hi> to the angle <hi rend="ital">DEH</hi> ; and, as <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> is to <hi rend="ital">DE</hi>
              , so is <hi rend="ital">BC</hi> to <hi rend="ital">EF</hi> , and <hi rend="ital">BG</hi> to <hi rend="ital">EH</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e7106"> And since, as <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> is to <hi rend="ital">DE</hi> , so is <hi rend="ital">BC</hi> to <hi rend="ital">EF</hi> , and the sides are proportional
              about equal angles, therefore the parallelogram <hi rend="ital">BM</hi> is similar to
              the parallelogram <hi rend="ital">EQ</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e7128"> For the same reason <hi rend="ital">BN</hi> is also similar to <hi rend="ital">ER</hi> , and <hi rend="ital">BK</hi> to <hi rend="ital">EO</hi> ; therefore the
              three parallelograms <hi rend="ital">MB</hi> , <hi rend="ital">BK</hi> , <hi rend="ital">BN</hi> are similar to the three <hi rend="ital">EQ</hi> , <hi rend="ital">EO</hi> , <hi rend="ital">ER</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e7162"> But the three parallelograms <hi rend="ital">MB</hi> , <hi rend="ital">BK</hi> , <hi rend="ital">BN</hi> are equal and similar to their three opposites, and the three
                <hi rend="ital">EQ</hi> , <hi rend="ital">EO</hi> , <hi rend="ital">ER</hi> are
              equal and similar to their three opposites. [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e7183" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.11.24">XI. 24</ref> ] </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e7187"> Therefore the solids <hi rend="ital">BGML</hi> , <hi rend="ital">EHQP</hi> are
              contained by similar planes equal in multitude. </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e7196"> Therefore the solid <hi rend="ital">BGML</hi> is similar to the solid <hi rend="ital">EHQP</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e7205"> But similar parallelepipedal solids are in the triplicate ratio of their
              corresponding sides. [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e7207" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.11.33">XI. 33</ref> ] 
            </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e7212"> Therefore the solid <hi rend="ital">BGML</hi> has to the solid <hi rend="ital">EHQP</hi> the ratio triplicate of that which the corresponding side <hi rend="ital">BC</hi> has to the corresponding side <hi rend="ital">EF</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e7227"> But, as the solid <hi rend="ital">BGML</hi> is to the solid <hi rend="ital">EHQP</hi> , so is the pyramid <hi rend="ital">ABCG</hi> to the pyramid <hi rend="ital">DEFH</hi> , inasmuch as the pyramid is a sixth part of the solid,
              because the prism which is half of the parallelepipedal solid [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e7241" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.11.28">XI. 28</ref> ] is also triple of the pyramid. [
                <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e7245" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.12.7">XII. 7</ref> ] </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e7249"> Therefore the pyramid <hi rend="ital">ABCG</hi> also has to the pyramid <hi rend="ital">DEFH</hi> the ratio triplicate of that which <hi rend="ital">BC</hi> has
              to <hi rend="ital">EF</hi> . Q. E. D. </p>
            <div xml:id="elem.12.8.p.1" type="porism" org="uniform" sample="complete">
              <head xml:id="ee-b12-Hd1e7266">PORISM.</head>
              <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e7269"> From this it is manifest that similar pyramids which have polygonal bases are also
                to one another in the triplicate ratio of their corresponding sides. </p>
              <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e7272"> For, if they are divided into the pyramids contained in them which have triangular
                bases, by virtue of the fact that the similar polygons forming their bases are also
                divided into similar triangles equal in multitude and corresponding to the wholes [
                  <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e7274" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.6.20">VI. 20</ref> ], then, as the one pyramid
                which has a triangular base in the one complete pyramid is to the one pyramid which
                has a triangular base in the other complete pyramid, so also will all the pyramids
                which have triangular bases contained in the one pyramid be to all the pyramids
                which have triangular bases contained in the other pyramid [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e7277" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.5.12">V. 12</ref> ], that is, the pyramid itself which has a polygonal
                base to the pyramid which has a polygonal base. </p>
              <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e7281"> But the pyramid which has a triangular base is to the pyramid which has a
                triangular base in the triplicate ratio of the corresponding sides; therefore also
                the pyramid which has a polygonal base has to the pyramid which has a similar base
                the ratio triplicate of that which the side has to the side. </p>
            </div>
          </div>
          
          <div xml:id="elem.12.9" n="9">
            <head xml:id="ee-b12-Hd1e7288">PROPOSITION 9.</head>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e7291">
              <hi rend="ital"> In equal pyramids which have triangular bases the bases are
                reciprocally proportional to the heights; and those pyramids in which the bases are
                reciprocally proportional to the heights are equal. </hi>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e7297"> For let there be equal pyramids which have the triangular bases <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> , <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi> and vertices the points <hi rend="ital">G</hi>
              , <hi rend="ital">H</hi> ; I say that in the pyramids <hi rend="ital">ABCG</hi> , <hi rend="ital">DEFH</hi> the bases are reciprocally proportional to the heights, that
              is, as the base <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> is to the base <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi> , so
              is the height of the pyramid <hi rend="ital">DEFH</hi> to the height of the pyramid
                <hi rend="ital">ABCG</hi> . <!-- <figure/> -->
            </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e7333"> For let the parallelepipedal solids <hi rend="ital">BGML</hi> , <hi rend="ital">EHQP</hi> be completed. </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e7342"> Now, since the pyramid <hi rend="ital">ABCG</hi> is equal to the pyramid <hi rend="ital">DEFH</hi> , and the solid <hi rend="ital">BGML</hi> is six times the
              pyramid <hi rend="ital">ABCG</hi> , and the solid <hi rend="ital">EHQP</hi> six times
              the pyramid <hi rend="ital">DEFH</hi> , therefore the solid <hi rend="ital">BGML</hi>
              is equal to the solid <hi rend="ital">EHQP</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e7371"> But in equal parallelepipedal solids the bases are reciprocally proportional to the
              heights; [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e7373" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.11.34">XI. 34</ref> ] therefore, as the
              base <hi rend="ital">BM</hi> is to the base <hi rend="ital">EQ</hi> , so is the height
              of the solid <hi rend="ital">EHQP</hi> to the height of the solid <hi rend="ital">BGML</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e7389"> But, as the base <hi rend="ital">BM</hi> is to <hi rend="ital">EQ</hi> , so is the
              triangle <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> to the triangle <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi> . [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e7403" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.1.34">I. 34</ref> ] </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e7407"> Therefore also, as the triangle <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> is to the triangle <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi> , so is the height of the solid <hi rend="ital">EHQP</hi> to
              the height of the solid <hi rend="ital">BGML</hi> . [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e7421" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.5.11">V. 11</ref> ] 
            </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e7425"> But the height of the solid <hi rend="ital">EHQP</hi> is the same with the height of
              the pyramid <hi rend="ital">DEFH</hi> , and the height of the solid <hi rend="ital">BGML</hi> is the same with the height of the pyramid <hi rend="ital">ABCG</hi> ,
              therefore, as the base <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> is to the base <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi> , so is the height of the pyramid <hi rend="ital">DEFH</hi> to the height
              of the pyramid <hi rend="ital">ABCG</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e7453"> Therefore in the pyramids <hi rend="ital">ABCG</hi> , <hi rend="ital">DEFH</hi> the
              bases are reciprocally proportional to the heights. </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e7462"> Next, in the pyramids <hi rend="ital">ABCG</hi> , <hi rend="ital">DEFH</hi> let the
              bases be reciprocally proportional to the heights; that is, as the base <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> is to the base <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi> , so let the height of
              the pyramid <hi rend="ital">DEFH</hi> be to the height of the pyramid <hi rend="ital">ABCG</hi> ; I say that the pyramid <hi rend="ital">ABCG</hi> is equal to the
              pyramid <hi rend="ital">DEFH</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e7491"> For, with the same construction, since, as the base <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> is to
              the base <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi> , so is the height of the pyramid <hi rend="ital">DEFH</hi> to the height of the pyramid <hi rend="ital">ABCG</hi> , while, as the
              base <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> is to the base <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi> , so is the
              parallelogram <hi rend="ital">BM</hi> to the parallelogram <hi rend="ital">EQ</hi> ,
              therefore also, as the parallelogram <hi rend="ital">BM</hi> is to the parallelogram
                <hi rend="ital">EQ</hi> , so is the height of the pyramid <hi rend="ital">DEFH</hi>
              to the height of the pyramid <hi rend="ital">ABCG</hi> . [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e7531" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.5.11">V. 11</ref> ] </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e7535"> But the height of the pyramid <hi rend="ital">DEFH</hi> is the same with the height
              of the parallelepiped <hi rend="ital">EHQP</hi> , and the height of the pyramid <hi rend="ital">ABCG</hi> is the same with the height of the parallelepiped <hi rend="ital">BGML</hi> ; therefore, as the base <hi rend="ital">BM</hi> is to the
              base <hi rend="ital">EQ</hi> , so is the height of the parallelepiped <hi rend="ital">EHQP</hi> to the height of the parallelepiped <hi rend="ital">BGML</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e7563"> But those parallelepipedal solids in which the bases are reciprocally proportional
              to the heights are equal; [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e7565" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.11.34">XI. 34</ref> ]
              therefore the parallelepipedal solid <hi rend="ital">BGML</hi> is equal to the
              parallelepipedal solid <hi rend="ital">EHQP</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e7575"> And the pyramid <hi rend="ital">ABCG</hi> is a sixth part of <hi rend="ital">BGML</hi> , and the pyramid <hi rend="ital">DEFH</hi> a sixth part of the
              parallelepiped <hi rend="ital">EHQP</hi> ;  therefore the pyramid <hi rend="ital">ABCG</hi> is equal to the pyramid <hi rend="ital">DEFH</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e7597">Therefore etc Q. E. D.</p>
          </div>
          <div xml:id="elem.12.10" n="10">
            <head xml:id="ee-b12-Hd1e7603">PROPOSITION 10.</head>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e7606">
              <hi rend="ital"> Any cone is a third part of the cylinder which has the same base with
                it and equal height. </hi>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e7612"> For let a cone have the same base, namely the circle <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> ,
              with a cylinder and equal height; I say that the cone is a third part of the cylinder,
              that is, that the cylinder is triple of the cone. </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e7618"> For if the cylinder is not triple of the cone, the cylinder will be either greater
              than triple or less than triple of the cone. <!-- <figure/> -->
            </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e7623"> First let it be greater than triple, and let the square <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> be
              inscribed in the circle <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> ; [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e7631" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.4.6">IV. 6</ref> ] then the square <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> is greater
              than the half of the circle <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e7642"> From the square <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> let there be set up a prism of equal
              height with the cylinder. </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e7648"> Then the prism so set up is greater than the half of the cylinder, 
              inasmuch as, if we also circumscribe a square about the circle <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e7653" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.4.7">IV. 7</ref> ], the square
              inscribed in the circle <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> is half of that circumscribed about
              it, and the solids set up from them are parallelepipedal prisms of equal height, while
              parallelepipedal solids which are of the same height are to one another as their
              bases; [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e7659" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.11.32">XI. 32</ref> ] therefore also the
              prism set up on the square <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> is half of the prism set up from
              the square circumscribed about the circle <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> ; [cf. <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e7669" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.11.28">XI. 28</ref> , or <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e7672" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.12.6 elem.12.7.p.1">XII. 6 and 7, Por.</ref> ] and the
              cylinder is less than the prism set up from the square circumscribed about the circle
                <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> ; therefore the prism set up from the square <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> and of equal height with the cylinder is greater than the half
              of the cylinder. </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e7682"> Let the circumferences <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> , <hi rend="ital">BC</hi> , <hi rend="ital">CD</hi> , <hi rend="ital">DA</hi> be bisected at the points <hi rend="ital">E</hi> , <hi rend="ital">F</hi> , <hi rend="ital">G</hi> , <hi rend="ital">H</hi> , and let <hi rend="ital">AE</hi> , <hi rend="ital">EB</hi> , <hi rend="ital">BF</hi> , <hi rend="ital">FC</hi> , <hi rend="ital">CG</hi> , <hi rend="ital">GD</hi> , <hi rend="ital">DH</hi> , <hi rend="ital">HA</hi> be joined;
              then each of the triangles <hi rend="ital">AEB</hi> , <hi rend="ital">BFC</hi> , <hi rend="ital">CGD</hi> , <hi rend="ital">DHA</hi> is greater than the half of that
              segment of the circle <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> which is about it, as we proved
              before. [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e7750" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.12.2">XII. 2</ref> ] </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e7754"> On each of the triangles <hi rend="ital">AEB</hi> , <hi rend="ital">BFC</hi> , <hi rend="ital">CGD</hi> , <hi rend="ital">DHA</hi> let prisms be set up of equal height
              with the cylinder; then each of the prisms so set up is greater than the half part of
              that segment of the cylinder which is about it, inasmuch as, if we draw through the
              points <hi rend="ital">E</hi> , <hi rend="ital">F</hi> , <hi rend="ital">G</hi> , <hi rend="ital">H</hi> parallels to <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> , <hi rend="ital">BC</hi> ,
                <hi rend="ital">CD</hi> , <hi rend="ital">DA</hi> , complete the parallelograms on
                <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> , <hi rend="ital">BC</hi> , <hi rend="ital">CD</hi> , <hi rend="ital">DA</hi> , and set up from them parallelepipedal solids of equal height
              with the cylinder, the prisms on the triangles <hi rend="ital">AEB</hi> , <hi rend="ital">BFC</hi> , <hi rend="ital">CGD</hi> , <hi rend="ital">DHA</hi> are
              halves of the several solids set up; and the segments of the cylinder are less than
              the parallelepipedal solids set up; hence also the prisms on the triangles <hi rend="ital">AEB</hi> , <hi rend="ital">BFC</hi> , <hi rend="ital">CGD</hi> , <hi rend="ital">DHA</hi> are greater than the half of the segments of the cylinder about
              them. </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e7833"> Thus, bisecting the circumferences that are left, joining  straight
              lines, setting up on each of the triangles prisms of equal height with the cylinder,
              and doing this continually, we shall leave some segments of the cylinder which will be
              less than the excess by which the cylinder exceeds the triple of the cone. [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e7835" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.10.1">X. 1</ref> ] </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e7839"> Let such segments be left, and let them be <hi rend="ital">AE</hi> , <hi rend="ital">EB</hi> , <hi rend="ital">BF</hi> , <hi rend="ital">FC</hi> , <hi rend="ital">CG</hi> , <hi rend="ital">GD</hi> , <hi rend="ital">DH</hi> , <hi rend="ital">HA</hi> ; therefore the remainder, the prism of which the polygon <hi rend="ital">AEBFCGDH</hi> is the base and the height is the same as that of the cylinder, is
              greater than triple of the cone. </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e7871"> But the prism of which the polygon <hi rend="ital">AEBFCGDH</hi> is the base and the
              height the same as that of the cylinder is triple of the pyramid of which the polygon
                <hi rend="ital">AEBFCGDH</hi> is the base and the vertex is the same as that of the
              cone; [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e7879" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.12.7.p.1">XII. 7, Por.</ref> ] therefore also
              the pyramid of which the polygon <hi rend="ital">AEBFCGDH</hi> is the base and the
              vertex is the same as that of the cone is greater than the cone which has the circle
                <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> as base. </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e7889"> But it is also less, for it is enclosed by it: which is impossible. </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e7892"> Therefore the cylinder is not greater than triple of the cone. </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e7895"> I say next that neither is the cylinder less than triple of the cone, </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e7898"> For, if possible, let the cylinder be less than triple of the cone, therefore,
              inversely, the cone is greater than a third part of the cylinder. </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e7901"> Let the square <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> be inscribed in the circle <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> ; therefore the square <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> is greater than the half
              of the circle <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e7917"> Now let there be set up from the square <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> a pyramid having
              the same vertex with the cone; therefore the pyramid so set up is greater than the
              half part of the cone, seeing that, as we proved before, if we circumscribe a square
                 about the circle, the square <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> will be half of
              the square circumscribed about the circle, and if we set up from the squares
              parallelepipedal solids of equal height with the cone, which are also called prisms,
              the solid set up from the square <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> will be half of that set up
              from the square circumscribed about the circle; for they are to one another as their
              bases. [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e7928" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.11.32">XI. 32</ref> ] </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e7932"> Hence also the thirds of them are in that ratio; therefore also the pyramid of which
              the square <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> is the base is half of the pyramid set up from
              the square circumscribed about the circle. </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e7938"> And the pyramid set up from the square about the circle is greater than the cone,
              for it encloses it. </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e7941"> Therefore the pyramid of which the square <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> is the base and
              the vertex is the same with that of the cone is greater than the half of the cone. </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e7947"> Let the circumferences <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> , <hi rend="ital">BC</hi> , <hi rend="ital">CD</hi> , <hi rend="ital">DA</hi> be bisected at the points <hi rend="ital">E</hi> , <hi rend="ital">F</hi> , <hi rend="ital">G</hi> , <hi rend="ital">H</hi> , and let <hi rend="ital">AE</hi> , <hi rend="ital">EB</hi> , <hi rend="ital">BF</hi> , <hi rend="ital">FC</hi> , <hi rend="ital">CG</hi> , <hi rend="ital">GD</hi> , <hi rend="ital">DH</hi> , <hi rend="ital">HA</hi> be joined;
              therefore also each of the triangles <hi rend="ital">AEB</hi> , <hi rend="ital">BFC</hi> , <hi rend="ital">CGD</hi> , <hi rend="ital">DHA</hi> is greater than the
              half part of that segment of the circle <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> which is about it. </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e8016"> Now, on each of the triangles <hi rend="ital">AEB</hi> , <hi rend="ital">BFC</hi> ,
                <hi rend="ital">CGD</hi> , <hi rend="ital">DHA</hi> let pyramids be set up which
              have the same vertex as the cone; therefore also each of the pyramids so set up is, in
              the same manner, greater than the half part of that segment of the cone which is about
              it. </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e8032"> Thus, by bisecting the circumferences that are left, joining straight lines, setting
              up on each of the triangles a pyramid which has the same vertex as the cone, and doing
              this continually, we shall leave some segments of the cone which will be less than the
              excess by which the cone exceeds the third part of the cylinder. [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e8034" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.10.1">X. 1</ref> ] </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e8038"> Let such be left, and let them be the segments on <hi rend="ital">AE</hi> , <hi rend="ital">EB</hi> , <hi rend="ital">BF</hi> , <hi rend="ital">FC</hi> , <hi rend="ital">CG</hi> , <hi rend="ital">GD</hi> , <hi rend="ital">DH</hi> , <hi rend="ital">HA</hi> ;  therefore the remainder, the pyramid of which
              the polygon <hi rend="ital">AEBFCGDH</hi> is the base and the vertex the same with
              that of the cone, is greater than a third part of the cylinder. </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e8069"> But the pyramid of which the polygon <hi rend="ital">AEBFCGDH</hi> is the base and
              the vertex the same with that of the cone is a third part of the prism of which the
              polygon <hi rend="ital">AEBFCGDH</hi> is the base and the height is the same with that
              of the cylinder; therefore the prism of which the polygon <hi rend="ital">AEBFCGDH</hi> is the base and the height is the same with that of the cylinder is
              greater than the cylinder of which the circle <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> is the base. </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e8084"> But it is also less, for it is enclosed by it: which is impossible. </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e8087"> Therefore the cylinder is not less than triple of the cone. </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e8090"> But it was proved that neither is it greater than triple; therefore the cylinder is
              triple of the cone; hence the cone is a third part of the cylinder. </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e8094">Therefore etc. Q. E. D.</p>
          </div>
          
          <div xml:id="elem.12.11" n="11">
            <head xml:id="ee-b12-Hd1e8101">PROPOSITION 11.</head>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e8104">
              <hi rend="ital"> Cones and cylinders which are of the same height are to one another
                as their bases. </hi>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e8110"> Let there be cones and cylinders of the same height, let the circles <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> , <hi rend="ital">EFGH</hi> be their bases, <hi rend="ital">KL</hi> , <hi rend="ital">MN</hi> their axes and <hi rend="ital">AC</hi> , <hi rend="ital">EG</hi>
              the diameters of their bases; I say that, as the circle <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> is
              to the circle <hi rend="ital">EFGH</hi> , so is the cone <hi rend="ital">AL</hi> to
              the cone <hi rend="ital">EN</hi> . <!-- <figure/> -->
            </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e8146"> For, if not, then, as the circle <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> is to the circle <hi rend="ital">EFGH</hi> , so will the cone <hi rend="ital">AL</hi> be either to some
              solid less than the cone <hi rend="ital">EN</hi> or to a greater. </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e8161"> First, let it be in that ratio to a less solid <hi rend="ital">O</hi> , and let the
              solid <hi rend="ital">X</hi> be equal to that by which the solid <hi rend="ital">O</hi> is less than the cone <hi rend="ital">EN</hi> ; therefore the cone <hi rend="ital">EN</hi> is equal to the solids <hi rend="ital">O</hi> , <hi rend="ital">X</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e8187"> Let the square <hi rend="ital">EFGH</hi> be inscribed in the circle <hi rend="ital">EFGH</hi> ; therefore the square is greater than the half of the circle. </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e8196"> Let there be set up from the square <hi rend="ital">EFGH</hi> a pyramid of equal
              height with the cone; therefore the pyramid so set up is greater than the half of the
              cone, inasmuch as, if we circumscribe a square about the circle, and set up from it a
              pyramid of equal height with the cone, the inscribed pyramid is half of the
              circumscribed pyramid, for they are to one another as their bases, [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e8201" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.12.6">XII. 6</ref> ] while the cone is less than the
              circumscribed pyramid. 
            </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e8205"> Let the circumferences <hi rend="ital">EF</hi> , <hi rend="ital">FG</hi> , <hi rend="ital">GH</hi> , <hi rend="ital">HE</hi> be bisected at the points <hi rend="ital">P</hi> , <hi rend="ital">Q</hi> , <hi rend="ital">R</hi> , <hi rend="ital">S</hi> , and let <hi rend="ital">HP</hi> , <hi rend="ital">PE</hi> , <hi rend="ital">EQ</hi> , <hi rend="ital">QF</hi> , <hi rend="ital">FR</hi> , <hi rend="ital">RG</hi> , <hi rend="ital">GS</hi> , <hi rend="ital">SH</hi> be joined. </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e8258"> Therefore each of the triangles <hi rend="ital">HPE</hi> , <hi rend="ital">EQF</hi>
              , <hi rend="ital">FRG</hi> , <hi rend="ital">GSH</hi> is greater than the half of that
              segment of the circle which is about it. </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e8273"> On each of the triangles <hi rend="ital">HPE</hi> , <hi rend="ital">EQF</hi> , <hi rend="ital">FRG</hi> , <hi rend="ital">GSH</hi> let there be set up a pyramid of
              equal height with the cone; therefore, also, each of the pyramids so set up is greater
              than the half of that segment of the cone which is about it. </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e8288"> Thus, bisecting the circumferences which are left, joining straight lines, setting
              up on each of the triangles pyramids of equal height with the cone, and doing this
              continually, we shall leave some segments of the cone which will be less than the
              solid <hi rend="ital">X</hi> . [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e8293" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.10.1">X. 1</ref> ] </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e8298"> Let such be left, and let them be the segments on <hi rend="ital">HP</hi> , <hi rend="ital">PE</hi> , <hi rend="ital">EQ</hi> , <hi rend="ital">QF</hi> , <hi rend="ital">FR</hi> , <hi rend="ital">RG</hi> , <hi rend="ital">GS</hi> , <hi rend="ital">SH</hi> ; therefore the remainder, the pyramid of which the polygon <hi rend="ital">HPEQFRGS</hi> is the base and the height the same with that of the cone,
              is greater than the solid <hi rend="ital">O</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e8332"> Let there also be inscribed in the circle <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> the polygon <hi rend="ital">DTAUBVCW</hi> similar and similarly situated to the polygon <hi rend="ital">HPEQFRGS</hi> , and on it let a pyramid be set up of equal height with
              the cone <hi rend="ital">AL</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e8347"> Since then, as the square on <hi rend="ital">AC</hi> is to the square on <hi rend="ital">EG</hi> , so is the polygon <hi rend="ital">DTAUBVCW</hi> to the polygon
                <hi rend="ital">HPEQFRGS</hi> , [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e8361" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.12.1">XII. 1</ref>
              ] while, as the square on <hi rend="ital">AC</hi> is to the square on <hi rend="ital">EG</hi> , so is the circle <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> to the circle <hi rend="ital">EFGH</hi> , [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e8377" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.12.2">XII. 2</ref> ] therefore also,
              as the circle <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> is to the circle <hi rend="ital">EFGH</hi> ,
              so is the polygon <hi rend="ital">DTAUBVCW</hi> to the polygon <hi rend="ital">HPEQFRGS</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e8394"> But, as the circle <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> is to the circle <hi rend="ital">EFGH</hi> , so is the cone <hi rend="ital">AL</hi> to the solid <hi rend="ital">O</hi> , and, as the polygon <hi rend="ital">DTAUBVCW</hi> is to the polygon <hi rend="ital">HPEQFRGS</hi> , so is the pyramid of which the polygon <hi rend="ital">DTAUBVCW</hi> is the base and the point <hi rend="ital">L</hi> the vertex to the
              pyramid of which the polygon <hi rend="ital">HPEQFRGS</hi> is the base and the point
                <hi rend="ital">N</hi> the vertex. [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e8427" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.12.6">XII.
                6</ref> ] 
            </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e8431"> Therefore also, as the cone <hi rend="ital">AL</hi> is to the solid <hi rend="ital">O</hi> , so is the pyramid of which the polygon <hi rend="ital">DTAUBVCW</hi> is
              the base and the point <hi rend="ital">L</hi> the vertex to the pyramid of which the
              polygon <hi rend="ital">HPEQFRGS</hi> is the base and the point <hi rend="ital">N</hi>
              the vertex; [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e8452" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.5.11">V. 11</ref> ] therefore,
              alternately, as the cone <hi rend="ital">AL</hi> is to the pyramid in it, so is the
              solid <hi rend="ital">O</hi> to the pyramid in the cone <hi rend="ital">EN</hi> . [
                <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e8464" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.5.16">V. 16</ref> ] </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e8468"> But the cone <hi rend="ital">AL</hi> is greater than the pyramid in it; therefore
              the solid <hi rend="ital">O</hi> is also greater than the pyramid in the cone <hi rend="ital">EN</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e8481">But it is also less: which is absurd.</p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e8484"> Therefore the cone <hi rend="ital">AL</hi> is not to any solid less than the cone
                <hi rend="ital">EN</hi> as the circle <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> is to the circle <hi rend="ital">EFGH</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e8499"> Similarly we can prove that neither is the cone <hi rend="ital">EN</hi> to any solid
              less than the cone <hi rend="ital">AL</hi> as the circle <hi rend="ital">EFGH</hi> is
              to the circle <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e8514"> I say next that neither is the cone <hi rend="ital">AL</hi> to any solid greater
              than the cone <hi rend="ital">EN</hi> as the circle <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> is to
              the circle <hi rend="ital">EFGH</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e8529"> For, if possible, let it be in that ratio to a greater solid <hi rend="ital">O</hi>
              ; therefore, inversely, as the circle <hi rend="ital">EFGH</hi> is to the circle <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> , so is the solid <hi rend="ital">O</hi> to the cone <hi rend="ital">AL</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e8547"> But, as the solid <hi rend="ital">O</hi> is to the cone <hi rend="ital">AL</hi> , so
              is the cone <hi rend="ital">EN</hi> to some solid less than the cone <hi rend="ital">AL</hi> ; therefore also, as the circle <hi rend="ital">EFGH</hi> is to the circle
                <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> , so is the cone <hi rend="ital">EN</hi> to some solid
              less than the cone <hi rend="ital">AL</hi> : which was proved impossible. </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e8576"> Therefore the cone <hi rend="ital">AL</hi> is not to any solid greater than the cone
                <hi rend="ital">EN</hi> as the circle <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> is to the circle <hi rend="ital">EFGH</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e8591"> But it was proved that neither is it in this ratio to a less solid; therefore, as
              the circle <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> is to the circle <hi rend="ital">EFGH</hi> , so
              is the cone <hi rend="ital">AL</hi> to the cone <hi rend="ital">EN</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e8606"> But, as the cone is to the cone, so is the cylinder to the cylinder, for each is
              triple of each; [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e8608" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.12.10">XII. 10</ref> ] 
            </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e8612"> Therefore also, as the circle <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> is to the circle <hi rend="ital">EFGH</hi> , so are the cylinders on them which are of equal height. </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e8621">Therefore etc. Q. E. D.</p>
          </div>
          
          <div xml:id="elem.12.12" n="12">
            <head xml:id="ee-b12-Hd1e8627">PROPOSITION 12.</head>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e8630">
              <hi rend="ital"> Similar cones and cylinders are to one another in the triplicate
                ratio of the diameters in their bases. </hi>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e8636"> Let there be similar cones and cylinders, let the circles <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi>
              , <hi rend="ital">EFGH</hi> be their bases, <hi rend="ital">BD</hi> , <hi rend="ital">FH</hi> the diameters of the bases, and <hi rend="ital">KL</hi> , <hi rend="ital">MN</hi> the axes of the cones and cylinders; I say that the cone of which the
              circle <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> is the base and the point <hi rend="ital">L</hi> the
              vertex has to the cone of which the circle <hi rend="ital">EFGH</hi> is the base and
              the point <hi rend="ital">N</hi> the vertex the ratio triplicate of that which <hi rend="ital">BD</hi> has to <hi rend="ital">FH</hi> . <!-- <figure/> -->
            </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e8679"> For, if the cone <hi rend="ital">ABCDL</hi> has not to the cone <hi rend="ital">EFGHN</hi> the ratio triplicate of that which <hi rend="ital">BD</hi> has to <hi rend="ital">FH</hi> , the cone <hi rend="ital">ABCDL</hi> will have that triplicate
              ratio either to some solid less than the cone <hi rend="ital">EFGHN</hi> or to a
              greater. </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e8701"> First, let it have that triplicate ratio to a less solid <hi rend="ital">O</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e8708"> Let the square <hi rend="ital">EFGH</hi> be inscribed in the circle <hi rend="ital">EFGH</hi> ; [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e8716" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.4.6">IV. 6</ref> ] therefore the
              square <hi rend="ital">EFGH</hi> is greater than the half of the circle <hi rend="ital">EFGH</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e8726"> Now let there be set up on the square <hi rend="ital">EFGH</hi> a pyramid having the
              same vertex with the cone; therefore the pyramid so set up is greater than the half
              part of the cone. 
            </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e8732"> Let the circumferences <hi rend="ital">EF</hi> , <hi rend="ital">FG</hi> , <hi rend="ital">GH</hi> , <hi rend="ital">HE</hi> be bisected at the points <hi rend="ital">P</hi> , <hi rend="ital">Q</hi> , <hi rend="ital">R</hi> , <hi rend="ital">S</hi> , and let <hi rend="ital">EP</hi> , <hi rend="ital">PF</hi> , <hi rend="ital">FQ</hi> , <hi rend="ital">QG</hi> , <hi rend="ital">GR</hi> , <hi rend="ital">RH</hi> , <hi rend="ital">HS</hi> , <hi rend="ital">SE</hi> be joined. </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e8785"> Therefore each of the triangles <hi rend="ital">EPF</hi> , <hi rend="ital">FQG</hi>
              , <hi rend="ital">GRH</hi> , <hi rend="ital">HSE</hi> is also greater than the half
              part of that segment of the circle <hi rend="ital">EFGH</hi> which is about it. </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e8803"> Now on each of the triangles <hi rend="ital">EPF</hi> , <hi rend="ital">FQG</hi> ,
                <hi rend="ital">GRH</hi> , <hi rend="ital">HSE</hi> let a pyramid be set up having
              the same vertex with the cone; therefore each of the pyramids so set up is also
              greater than the half part of that segment of the cone which is about it. </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e8818"> Thus, bisecting the circumferences so left, joining straight lines, setting up on
              each of the triangles pyramids having the same vertex with the cone, and doing this
              continually, we shall leave some segments of the cone which will be less than the
              excess by which the cone <hi rend="ital">EFGHN</hi> exceeds the solid <hi rend="ital">O</hi> . [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e8826" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.10.1">X. 1</ref> ] </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e8831"> Let such be left, and let them be the segments on <hi rend="ital">EP</hi> , <hi rend="ital">PF</hi> , <hi rend="ital">FQ</hi> , <hi rend="ital">QG</hi> , <hi rend="ital">GR</hi> , <hi rend="ital">RH</hi> , <hi rend="ital">HS</hi> , <hi rend="ital">SE</hi> ; therefore the remainder, the pyramid of which the polygon <hi rend="ital">EPFQGRHS</hi> is the base and the point <hi rend="ital">N</hi> the
              vertex, is greater than the solid <hi rend="ital">O</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e8868"> Let there be also inscribed in the circle <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> the polygon <hi rend="ital">ATBUCVDW</hi> similar and similarly situated to the polygon <hi rend="ital">EPFQGRHS</hi> , and let there be set up on the polygon <hi rend="ital">ATBUCVDW</hi> a pyramid having the same vertex with the cone; of the triangles
              containing the pyramid of which the polygon <hi rend="ital">ATBUCVDW</hi> is the base
              and the point <hi rend="ital">L</hi> the vertex let <hi rend="ital">LBT</hi> be one,
              and of the triangles containing the pyramid of which the polygon <hi rend="ital">EPFQGRHS</hi> is the base and the point <hi rend="ital">N</hi> the vertex let <hi rend="ital">NFP</hi> be one; and let <hi rend="ital">KT</hi> , <hi rend="ital">MP</hi> be joined. </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e8909"> Now, since the cone <hi rend="ital">ABCDL</hi> is similar to the cone <hi rend="ital">EFGHN</hi> , therefore, as <hi rend="ital">BD</hi> is to <hi rend="ital">FH</hi> , so is the axis <hi rend="ital">KL</hi> to the axis <hi rend="ital">MN</hi> . [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e8930" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.11.def.24">XI. Def. 24</ref> ] 
            </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e8934"> But, as <hi rend="ital">BD</hi> is to <hi rend="ital">FH</hi> , so is <hi rend="ital">BK</hi> to <hi rend="ital">FM</hi> ; therefore also, as <hi rend="ital">BK</hi> is to <hi rend="ital">FM</hi> , so is <hi rend="ital">KL</hi> to <hi rend="ital">MN</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e8962"> And, alternately, as <hi rend="ital">BK</hi> is to <hi rend="ital">KL</hi> , so is
                <hi rend="ital">FM</hi> to <hi rend="ital">MN</hi> . [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e8976" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.5.16">V. 16</ref> ] </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e8980"> And the sides are proportional about equal angles, namely the angles <hi rend="ital">BKL</hi> , <hi rend="ital">FMN</hi> ; therefore the triangle <hi rend="ital">BKL</hi> is similar to the triangle <hi rend="ital">FMN</hi> . [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e8994" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.6.6">VI. 6</ref> ] </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e8999"> Again, since, as <hi rend="ital">BK</hi> is to <hi rend="ital">KT</hi> , so is <hi rend="ital">FM</hi> to <hi rend="ital">MP</hi> , and they are about equal angles,
              namely the angles <hi rend="ital">BKT</hi> , <hi rend="ital">FMP</hi> , inasmuch as,
              whatever part the angle <hi rend="ital">BKT</hi> is of the four right angles at the
              centre <hi rend="ital">K</hi> , the same part also is the angle <hi rend="ital">FMP</hi> of the four right angles at the centre <hi rend="ital">M</hi> ; since then
              the sides are proportional about equal angles, therefore the triangle <hi rend="ital">BKT</hi> is similar to the triangle <hi rend="ital">FMP</hi> . [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e9039" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.6.6">VI. 6</ref> ] </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e9043"> Again, since it was proved that, as <hi rend="ital">BK</hi> is to <hi rend="ital">KL</hi> , so is <hi rend="ital">FM</hi> to <hi rend="ital">MN</hi> , while <hi rend="ital">BK</hi> is equal to <hi rend="ital">KT</hi> , and <hi rend="ital">FM</hi> to <hi rend="ital">PM</hi> , therefore, as <hi rend="ital">TK</hi> is to
                <hi rend="ital">KL</hi> , so is <hi rend="ital">PM</hi> to <hi rend="ital">MN</hi> ;
              and the sides are proportional about equal angles, namely the angles <hi rend="ital">TKL</hi> , <hi rend="ital">PMN</hi> , for they are right; therefore the triangle
                <hi rend="ital">LKT</hi> is similar to the triangle <hi rend="ital">NMP</hi> . [
                <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e9095" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.6.6">VI. 6</ref> ] </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e9099"> And since, owing to the similarity of the triangles <hi rend="ital">LKB</hi> , <hi rend="ital">NMF</hi> , as <hi rend="ital">LB</hi> is to <hi rend="ital">BK</hi> , so
              is <hi rend="ital">NF</hi> to <hi rend="ital">FM</hi> , and, owing to the similarity
              of the triangles <hi rend="ital">BKT</hi> , <hi rend="ital">FMP</hi> , as <hi rend="ital">KB</hi> is to <hi rend="ital">BT</hi> , so is <hi rend="ital">MF</hi> to
                <hi rend="ital">FP</hi> , therefore, <hi rend="ital">ex aequali</hi> , as <hi rend="ital">LB</hi> is to <hi rend="ital">BT</hi> , so is <hi rend="ital">NF</hi> to
                <hi rend="ital">FP</hi> . [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e9155" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.5.22">V. 22</ref> ] </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e9159"> Again since, owing to the similarity of the triangles <hi rend="ital">LTK</hi> , <hi rend="ital">NPM</hi> , as <hi rend="ital">LT</hi> is to <hi rend="ital">TK</hi> , so
              is <hi rend="ital">NP</hi> to <hi rend="ital">PM</hi> , and, owing to the similarity
              of the triangles <hi rend="ital">TKB</hi> , <hi rend="ital">PMF</hi> , as <hi rend="ital">KT</hi> is to <hi rend="ital">TB</hi> , so is <hi rend="ital">MP</hi> to
                <hi rend="ital">PF</hi> ; therefore, <hi rend="ital">ex aequali</hi> , as <hi rend="ital">LT</hi> is to <hi rend="ital">TB</hi> , so is <hi rend="ital">NP</hi> to
                <hi rend="ital">PF</hi> . [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e9215" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.5.22">V. 22</ref> ] 
            </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e9219"> But it was also proved that, as <hi rend="ital">TB</hi> is to <hi rend="ital">BL</hi> , so is <hi rend="ital">PF</hi> to <hi rend="ital">FN</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e9234"> Therefore, <foreign xml:lang="la">ex aequali</foreign> , as <hi rend="ital">TL</hi> is
              to <hi rend="ital">LB</hi> , so is <hi rend="ital">PN</hi> to <hi rend="ital">NF</hi>
              . [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e9252" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.5.22">V. 22</ref> ] </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e9257"> Therefore in the triangles <hi rend="ital">LTB</hi> , <hi rend="ital">NPF</hi> the
              sides are proportional; therefore the triangles <hi rend="ital">LTB</hi> , <hi rend="ital">NPF</hi> are equiangular; [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e9271" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.6.5">VI.
                5</ref> ] hence they are also similar. [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e9275" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.6.def.1">VI. Def. I</ref> ] </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e9279"> Therefore the pyramid of which the triangle <hi rend="ital">BKT</hi> is the base and
              the point <hi rend="ital">L</hi> the vertex is also similar to the pyramid of which
              the triangle <hi rend="ital">FMP</hi> is the base and the point <hi rend="ital">N</hi>
              the vertex, for they are contained by similar planes equal in multitude. [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e9293" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.11.def.9">XI. Def. 9</ref> ] </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e9297"> But similar pyramids which have triangular bases are to one another in the
              triplicate ratio of their corresponding sides. [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e9299" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.12.8">XII. 8</ref> ] </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e9303"> Therefore the pyramid <hi rend="ital">BKTL</hi> has to the pyramid <hi rend="ital">FMPN</hi> the ratio triplicate of that which <hi rend="ital">BK</hi> has to <hi rend="ital">FM</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e9318"> Similarly, by joining straight lines from <hi rend="ital">A</hi> , <hi rend="ital">W</hi> , <hi rend="ital">D</hi> , <hi rend="ital">V</hi> , <hi rend="ital">C</hi> ,
                <hi rend="ital">U</hi> to <hi rend="ital">K</hi> , and from <hi rend="ital">E</hi> ,
                <hi rend="ital">S</hi> , <hi rend="ital">H</hi> , <hi rend="ital">R</hi> , <hi rend="ital">G</hi> , <hi rend="ital">Q</hi> to <hi rend="ital">M</hi> , and setting
              up on each of the triangles pyramids which have the same vertex with the cones, we can
              prove that each of the similarly arranged pyramids will also have to each similarly
              arranged pyramid the ratio triplicate of that which the corresponding side <hi rend="ital">BK</hi> has to the corresponding side <hi rend="ital">FM</hi> , that is,
              which <hi rend="ital">BD</hi> has to <hi rend="ital">FH</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e9378"> And, as one of the antecedents is to one of the consequents, so are all the
              antecedents to all the consequents; [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e9380" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.5.12">V.
                12</ref> ] therefore also, as the pyramid <hi rend="ital">BKTL</hi> is to the
              pyramid <hi rend="ital">FMPN</hi> , so is the whole pyramid of which the polygon <hi rend="ital">ATBUCVDW</hi> is the base and the point <hi rend="ital">L</hi> the
              vertex to the whole pyramid of which the polygon <hi rend="ital">EPFQGRHS</hi> is the
              base and the point <hi rend="ital">N</hi> the vertex; hence also the pyramid of which
                <hi rend="ital">ATBUCVDW</hi> is the base and the point <hi rend="ital">L</hi> the
              vertex has to the pyramid of which the polygon <hi rend="ital">EPFQGRHS</hi> is the
              base and the point <hi rend="ital">N</hi> the vertex the ratio triplicate of that
              which <hi rend="ital">BD</hi> has to <hi rend="ital">FH</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e9423"> But, by hypothesis, the cone of which the circle <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi>
               is the base and the point <hi rend="ital">L</hi> the vertex has also to
              the solid <hi rend="ital">O</hi> the ratio triplicate of that which <hi rend="ital">BD</hi> has to <hi rend="ital">FH</hi> ; therefore, as the cone of which the circle
                <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> is the base and the point <hi rend="ital">L</hi> the
              vertex is to the solid <hi rend="ital">O</hi> , so is the pyramid of which the polygon
                <hi rend="ital">ATBUCVDW</hi> is the base and <hi rend="ital">L</hi> the vertex to
              the pyramid of which the polygon <hi rend="ital">EPFQGRHS</hi> is the base and the
              point <hi rend="ital">N</hi> the vertex; therefore, alternately, as the cone of which
              the circle <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> is the base and <hi rend="ital">L</hi> the vertex
              is to the pyramid contained in it of which the polygon <hi rend="ital">ATBUCVDW</hi>
              is the base and <hi rend="ital">L</hi> the vertex, so is the solid <hi rend="ital">O</hi> to the pyramid of which the polygon <hi rend="ital">EPFQGRHS</hi> is the
              base and <hi rend="ital">N</hi> the vertex. [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e9485" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.5.16">V.
                16</ref> ] </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e9489"> But the said cone is greater than the pyramid in it; for it encloses it. </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e9492"> Therefore the solid <hi rend="ital">O</hi> is also greater than the pyramid of which
              the polygon <hi rend="ital">EPFQGRHS</hi> is the base and <hi rend="ital">N</hi> the
              vertex. </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e9504">But it is also less: which is impossible.</p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e9507"> Therefore the cone of which the circle <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> is the base and <hi rend="ital">L</hi> the vertex has not to any solid less than the cone of which the
              circle <hi rend="ital">EFGH</hi> is the base and the point <hi rend="ital">N</hi> the
              vertex the ratio triplicate of that which <hi rend="ital">BD</hi> has to <hi rend="ital">FH</hi> : </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e9529"> Similarly we can prove that neither has the cone <hi rend="ital">EFGHN</hi> to any
              solid less than the cone <hi rend="ital">ABCDL</hi> the ratio triplicate of that which
                <hi rend="ital">FH</hi> has to <hi rend="ital">BD</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e9545"> I say next that neither has the cone <hi rend="ital">ABCDL</hi> to any solid greater
              than the cone <hi rend="ital">EFGHN</hi> the ratio triplicate of that which <hi rend="ital">BD</hi> has to <hi rend="ital">FH</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e9560"> For, if possible, let it have that ratio to a greater solid <hi rend="ital">O</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e9566"> Therefore, inversely, the solid <hi rend="ital">O</hi> has to the cone <hi rend="ital">ABCDL</hi> the ratio triplicate of that which <hi rend="ital">FH</hi>
              has to <hi rend="ital">BD</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e9581"> But, as the solid <hi rend="ital">O</hi> is to the cone <hi rend="ital">ABCDL</hi> ,
              so is the cone <hi rend="ital">EFGHN</hi> to some solid less than the cone <hi rend="ital">ABCDL</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e9596"> Therefore the cone <hi rend="ital">EFGHN</hi> also has to some solid less than the
              cone <hi rend="ital">ABCDL</hi> the ratio triplicate of that which <hi rend="ital">FH</hi> has to <hi rend="ital">BD</hi> : which was proved impossible. 
            </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e9611"> Therefore the cone <hi rend="ital">ABCDL</hi> has not to any solid greater than the
              cone <hi rend="ital">EFGHN</hi> the ratio triplicate of that which <hi rend="ital">BD</hi> has to <hi rend="ital">FH</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e9627"> But it was proved that neither has it this ratio to a less solid than the cone <hi rend="ital">EFGHN</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e9633"> Therefore the cone <hi rend="ital">ABCDL</hi> has to the cone <hi rend="ital">EFGHN</hi> the ratio triplicate of that which <hi rend="ital">BD</hi> has to <hi rend="ital">FH</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e9648"> But, as the cone is to the cone, so is the cylinder to the cylinder, for the
              cylinder which is on the same base as the cone and of equal height with it is triple
              of the cone; [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e9650" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.12.10">XII. 10</ref> ] therefore the
              cylinder also has to the cylinder the ratio triplicate of that which <hi rend="ital">BD</hi> has to <hi rend="ital">FH</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e9660">Therefore etc. Q. E. D.</p>
          </div>
          <div xml:id="elem.12.13" n="13">
            <head xml:id="ee-b12-Hd1e9666">PROPOSITION 13.</head>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e9669">
              <hi rend="ital"> If a cylinder be cut by a plane which is parallel to its opposite
                planes, then, as the cylinder is to the cylinder, so will the axis be to the axis.
              </hi>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e9675"> For let the cylinder <hi rend="ital">AD</hi> be cut by the plane <hi rend="ital">GH</hi> which is parallel to the opposite planes <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> , <hi rend="ital">CD</hi> , and let the plane <hi rend="ital">GH</hi> meet the axis at the
              point <hi rend="ital">K</hi> ; I say that, as the cylinder <hi rend="ital">BG</hi> is
              to the cylinder <hi rend="ital">GD</hi> , so is the axis <hi rend="ital">EK</hi> to
              the axis <hi rend="ital">KF</hi> . <!-- <figure/> -->
            </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e9711"> For let the axis <hi rend="ital">EF</hi> be produced in both directions to the
              points <hi rend="ital">L</hi> , <hi rend="ital">M</hi> , and let there be set out any
              number whatever of axes <hi rend="ital">EN</hi> , <hi rend="ital">NL</hi> equal to the
              axis <hi rend="ital">EK</hi> , and any number whatever <hi rend="ital">FO</hi> , <hi rend="ital">OM</hi> equal to <hi rend="ital">FK</hi> ; and let the cylinder <hi rend="ital">PW</hi> on the axis <hi rend="ital">LM</hi> be conceived of which the
              circles <hi rend="ital">PQ</hi> , <hi rend="ital">VW</hi> are the bases. </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e9755"> Let planes be carried through the points <hi rend="ital">N</hi> , <hi rend="ital">O</hi> parallel to <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> , <hi rend="ital">CD</hi> and to the
              bases of the cylinder <hi rend="ital">PW</hi> , and let them produce the circles <hi rend="ital">RS</hi> , <hi rend="ital">TU</hi> about the centres <hi rend="ital">N</hi> , <hi rend="ital">O</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e9787"> Then, since the axes <hi rend="ital">LN</hi> , <hi rend="ital">NE</hi> , <hi rend="ital">EK</hi> are equal to one another,  therefore the cylinders
                <hi rend="ital">QR</hi> , <hi rend="ital">RB</hi> , <hi rend="ital">BG</hi> are to
              one another as their bases. [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e9808" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.12.11">XII. 11</ref> ] </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e9812"> But the bases are equal; therefore the cylinders <hi rend="ital">QR</hi> , <hi rend="ital">RB</hi> , <hi rend="ital">BG</hi> are also equal to one another. </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e9824"> Since then the axes <hi rend="ital">LN</hi> , <hi rend="ital">NE</hi> , <hi rend="ital">EK</hi> are equal to one another, and the cylinders <hi rend="ital">QR</hi> , <hi rend="ital">RB</hi> , <hi rend="ital">BG</hi> are also equal to one
              another, and the multitude of the former is equal to the multitude of the latter,
              therefore, whatever multiple the axis <hi rend="ital">KL</hi> is of the axis <hi rend="ital">EK</hi> , the same multiple also will the cylinder <hi rend="ital">QG</hi> be of the cylinder <hi rend="ital">GB</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e9858"> For the same reason, whatever multiple the axis <hi rend="ital">MK</hi> is of the
              axis <hi rend="ital">KF</hi> , the same multiple also is the cylinder <hi rend="ital">WG</hi> of the cylinder <hi rend="ital">GD</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e9873"> And, if the axis <hi rend="ital">KL</hi> is equal to the axis <hi rend="ital">KM</hi> , the cylinder <hi rend="ital">QG</hi> will also be equal to the cylinder
                <hi rend="ital">GW</hi> , if the axis is greater than the axis, the cylinder will
              also be greater than the cylinder, and if less, less. </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e9888"> Thus, there being four magnitudes, the axes <hi rend="ital">EK</hi> , <hi rend="ital">KF</hi> and the cylinders <hi rend="ital">BG</hi> , <hi rend="ital">GD</hi> , there have been taken equimultiples of the axis <hi rend="ital">EK</hi>
              and of the cylinder <hi rend="ital">BG</hi> , namely the axis <hi rend="ital">LK</hi>
              and the cylinder <hi rend="ital">QG</hi> , and equimultiples of the axis <hi rend="ital">KF</hi> and of the cylinder <hi rend="ital">GD</hi> , namely the axis
                <hi rend="ital">KM</hi> and the cylinder <hi rend="ital">GW</hi> ; and it has been
              proved that, if the axis <hi rend="ital">KL</hi> is in excess of the axis <hi rend="ital">KM</hi> , the cylinder <hi rend="ital">QG</hi> is also in excess of the
              cylinder <hi rend="ital">GW</hi> , if equal, equal, and if less, less. </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e9942"> Therefore, as the axis <hi rend="ital">EK</hi> is to the axis <hi rend="ital">KF</hi> , so is the cylinder <hi rend="ital">BG</hi> to the cylinder <hi rend="ital">GD</hi> . [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e9956" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.5.def.5">V. Def. 5</ref> ]
              Q. E. D. </p>
          </div>
          <div xml:id="elem.12.14" n="14">
            <head xml:id="ee-b12-Hd1e9963">PROPOSITION 14.</head>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e9966">
              <hi rend="ital"> Cones and cylinders which are on equal bases are to one another as
                their heights. </hi>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e9972"> For let <hi rend="ital">EB</hi> , <hi rend="ital">FD</hi> be cylinders on equal
              bases, the circles <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> , <hi rend="ital">CD</hi> ; I say that, as
              the cylinder <hi rend="ital">EB</hi> is to the cylinder <hi rend="ital">FD</hi> , so
              is the axis <hi rend="ital">GH</hi> to the axis <hi rend="ital">KL</hi> . <!-- <figure/> -->
            </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e10002"> For let the axis <hi rend="ital">KL</hi> be produced to the point <hi rend="ital">N</hi> , let <hi rend="ital">LN</hi> be made equal to the axis <hi rend="ital">GH</hi> , and let the cylinder <hi rend="ital">CM</hi> be conceived about <hi rend="ital">LN</hi> as axis. </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e10024"> Since then the cylinders <hi rend="ital">EB</hi> , <hi rend="ital">CM</hi> are of
              the same height, they are to one another as their bases. [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e10032" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.12.11">XII. 11</ref> ] </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e10037"> But the bases are equal to one another; therefore the cylinders <hi rend="ital">EB</hi> , <hi rend="ital">CM</hi> are also equal. </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e10046"> And, since the cylinder <hi rend="ital">FM</hi> has been cut by the plane <hi rend="ital">CD</hi> which is parallel to its opposite planes, therefore, as the
              cylinder <hi rend="ital">CM</hi> is to the cylinder <hi rend="ital">FD</hi> , so is
              the axis <hi rend="ital">LN</hi> to the axis <hi rend="ital">KL</hi> . [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e10067" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.12.13">XII. 13</ref> ] </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e10071"> But the cylinder <hi rend="ital">CM</hi> is equal to the cylinder <hi rend="ital">EB</hi> , and the axis <hi rend="ital">LN</hi> to the axis <hi rend="ital">GH</hi>
              ; therefore, as the cylinder <hi rend="ital">EB</hi> is to the cylinder <hi rend="ital">FD</hi> , so is the axis <hi rend="ital">GH</hi> to the axis <hi rend="ital">KL</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e10099"> But, as the cylinder <hi rend="ital">EB</hi> is to the cylinder <hi rend="ital">FD</hi> , so is the cone <hi rend="ital">ABG</hi> to the cone <hi rend="ital">CDK</hi> . [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e10113" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.12.10">XII. 10</ref> ] </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e10117"> Therefore also, as the axis <hi rend="ital">GH</hi> is to the axis <hi rend="ital">KL</hi> , so is the cone <hi rend="ital">ABG</hi> to the cone <hi rend="ital">CDK</hi> and the cylinder <hi rend="ital">EB</hi> to the cylinder <hi rend="ital">FD</hi> . Q. E. D. </p>
          </div>
          
          <div xml:id="elem.12.15" n="15">
            <head xml:id="ee-b12-Hd1e10142">PROPOSITION 15.</head>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e10145">
              <hi rend="ital"> In equal cones and cylinders the bases are reciprocally proportional
                to the heights; and those cones and cylinders in which the bases are reciprocally
                proportional to the heights are equal. </hi>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e10151"> Let there be equal cones and cylinders of which the circles <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> , <hi rend="ital">EFGH</hi> are the bases; let <hi rend="ital">AC</hi> ,
                <hi rend="ital">EG</hi> be the diameters of the bases, and <hi rend="ital">KL</hi> ,
                <hi rend="ital">MN</hi> the axes, which are also the heights of the cones or
              cylinders; let the cylinders <hi rend="ital">AO</hi> , <hi rend="ital">EP</hi> be
              completed. </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e10179"> I say that in the cylinders <hi rend="ital">AO</hi> , <hi rend="ital">EP</hi> the
              bases are reciprocally proportional to the heights, that is, as the base <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> is to the base <hi rend="ital">EFGH</hi> , so is the height
                <hi rend="ital">MN</hi> to the height <hi rend="ital">KL</hi> . <!-- <figure/> -->
            </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e10203"> For the height <hi rend="ital">LK</hi> is either equal to the height <hi rend="ital">MN</hi> or not equal. </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e10213">First, let it be equal.</p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e10216"> Now the cylinder <hi rend="ital">AO</hi> is also equal to the cylinder <hi rend="ital">EP</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e10225"> But cones and cylinders which are of the same height are to one another as their
              bases; [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e10227" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.12.11">XII. 11</ref> ] therefore the base <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> is also equal to the base <hi rend="ital">EFGH</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e10237"> Hence also, reciprocally, as the base <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> is to the base <hi rend="ital">EFGH</hi> , so is the height <hi rend="ital">MN</hi> to the height <hi rend="ital">KL</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e10252"> Next, let the height <hi rend="ital">LK</hi> not be equal to <hi rend="ital">MN</hi>
              , but let <hi rend="ital">MN</hi> be greater; from the height <hi rend="ital">MN</hi>
              let <hi rend="ital">QN</hi> be cut off equal to <hi rend="ital">KL</hi> , through the
              point <hi rend="ital">Q</hi> let the cylinder <hi rend="ital">EP</hi> be cut by the
              plane <hi rend="ital">TUS</hi> parallel to the planes of the circles <hi rend="ital">EFGH</hi> , <hi rend="ital">RP</hi> ,  and let the cylinder <hi rend="ital">ES</hi> be conceived erected from the circle <hi rend="ital">EFGH</hi>
              as base and with height <hi rend="ital">NQ</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e10299"> Now, since the cylinder <hi rend="ital">AO</hi> is equal to the cylinder <hi rend="ital">EP</hi> , therefore, as the cylinder <hi rend="ital">AO</hi> is to the
              cylinder <hi rend="ital">ES</hi> , so is the cylinder <hi rend="ital">EP</hi> to the
              cylinder <hi rend="ital">ES</hi> . [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e10320" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.5.7">V. 7</ref> ] </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e10325"> But, as the cylinder <hi rend="ital">AO</hi> is to the cylinder <hi rend="ital">ES</hi> , so is the base <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> to the base <hi rend="ital">EFGH</hi> , for the cylinders <hi rend="ital">AO</hi> , <hi rend="ital">ES</hi> are
              of the same height; [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e10346" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.12.11">XII. 11</ref> ] and, as
              the cylinder <hi rend="ital">EP</hi> is to the cylinder <hi rend="ital">ES</hi> , so
              is the height <hi rend="ital">MN</hi> to the height <hi rend="ital">QN</hi> , for the
              cylinder <hi rend="ital">EP</hi> has been cut by a plane which is parallel to its
              opposite planes. [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e10365" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.12.13">XII. 13</ref> ] </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e10369"> Therefore also, as the base <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> is to the base <hi rend="ital">EFGH</hi> , so is the height <hi rend="ital">MN</hi> to the height <hi rend="ital">QN</hi> . [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e10383" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.5.11">V. 11</ref> ] </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e10387"> But the height <hi rend="ital">QN</hi> is equal to the height <hi rend="ital">KL</hi> ; therefore, as the base <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> is to the base <hi rend="ital">EFGH</hi> , so is the height <hi rend="ital">MN</hi> to the height <hi rend="ital">KL</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e10409"> Therefore in the cylinders <hi rend="ital">AO</hi> , <hi rend="ital">EP</hi> the
              bases are reciprocally proportional to the heights. </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e10418"> Next, in the cylinders <hi rend="ital">AO</hi> , <hi rend="ital">EP</hi> let the
              bases be reciprocally proportional to the heights, that is, as the base <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> is to the base <hi rend="ital">EFGH</hi> , so let the height
                <hi rend="ital">MN</hi> be to the height <hi rend="ital">KL</hi> ; I say that the
              cylinder <hi rend="ital">AO</hi> is equal to the cylinder <hi rend="ital">EP</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e10446"> For, with the same construction, since, as the base <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> is to
              the base <hi rend="ital">EFGH</hi> , so is the height <hi rend="ital">MN</hi> to the
              height <hi rend="ital">KL</hi> , while the height <hi rend="ital">KL</hi> is equal to
              the height <hi rend="ital">QN</hi> , therefore, as the base <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi>
              is to the base <hi rend="ital">EFGH</hi> , so is the height <hi rend="ital">MN</hi> to
              the height <hi rend="ital">QN</hi>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e10481"> But, as the base <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> is to the base <hi rend="ital">EFGH</hi>
              , so is the cylinder <hi rend="ital">AO</hi> to the cylinder <hi rend="ital">ES</hi> ,
              for they are of the same height; [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e10495" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.12.11">XII.
                11</ref> ] and, as the height <hi rend="ital">MN</hi> is to <hi rend="ital">QN</hi>
              , so is the cylinder <hi rend="ital">EP</hi> to the cylinder <hi rend="ital">ES</hi> ;
              [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e10511" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.12.13">XII. 13</ref> ] therefore, as the cylinder
                <hi rend="ital">AO</hi> is to the cylinder <hi rend="ital">ES</hi> , so is the
              cylinder <hi rend="ital">EP</hi> to the cylinder <hi rend="ital">ES</hi> . [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e10527" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.5.11">V. 11</ref> ] 
            </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e10531"> Therefore the cylinder <hi rend="ital">AO</hi> is equal to the cylinder <hi rend="ital">EP</hi> . [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e10539" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.5.9">V. 9</ref> ] </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e10543">And the same is true for the cones also. Q. E. D.</p>
          </div>
          <div xml:id="elem.12.16" n="16">
            <head xml:id="ee-b12-Hd1e10549">PROPOSITION 16.</head>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e10552">
              <hi rend="ital">Given two circles about the same centre</hi> , <hi rend="ital"> to
                inscribe in the greater circle an equilateral polygon with an even number of sides
                which does not touch the lesser circle. </hi>
              
            </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e10561"> Let <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> , <hi rend="ital">EFGH</hi> be the two given circles
              about the same centre <hi rend="ital">K</hi> ; thus it is required to inscribe in the
              greater circle <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> an equilateral polygon with an even number of
              sides which does not touch the circle <hi rend="ital">EFGH</hi> . <!-- <figure/> -->
            </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e10581"> For let the straight line <hi rend="ital">BKD</hi> be drawn through the centre <hi rend="ital">K</hi> , and from the point <hi rend="ital">G</hi> let <hi rend="ital">GA</hi> be drawn at right angles to the straight line <hi rend="ital">BD</hi> and
              carried through to <hi rend="ital">C</hi> ; therefore <hi rend="ital">AC</hi> touches
              the circle <hi rend="ital">EFGH</hi> . [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e10608" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.3.16.p.1">III. 16, Por.</ref> ] </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e10612"> Then, bisecting the circumference <hi rend="ital">BAD</hi> , bisecting the half of
              it, and doing this continually, we shall leave a circumference less than <hi rend="ital">AD</hi> . [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e10620" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.10.1">X. 1</ref> ] </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e10625"> Let such be left, and let it be <hi rend="ital">LD</hi> ; from <hi rend="ital">L</hi> let <hi rend="ital">LM</hi> be drawn perpendicular to <hi rend="ital">BD</hi> and carried through to <hi rend="ital">N</hi> , and let <hi rend="ital">LD</hi> , <hi rend="ital">DN</hi> be joined; therefore <hi rend="ital">LD</hi> is
              equal to <hi rend="ital">DN</hi> . [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e10655" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.3.3">III. 3</ref>
              , <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e10658" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.1.4">I. 4</ref> ] </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e10662"> Now, since <hi rend="ital">LN</hi> is parallel to <hi rend="ital">AC</hi> , and <hi rend="ital">AC</hi> touches the circle <hi rend="ital">EFGH</hi> , therefore <hi rend="ital">LN</hi> does not touch the circle <hi rend="ital">EFGH</hi> ; therefore
                <hi rend="ital">LD</hi> , <hi rend="ital">DN</hi> are far from touching the circle
                <hi rend="ital">EFGH</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e10693"> If then we fit into the circle <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> straight lines equal to the
              straight line <hi rend="ital">LD</hi> and placed continuously, there will be inscribed
              in the circle <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> an equilateral polygon with an even number of
              sides which does not touch the lesser circle <hi rend="ital">EFGH</hi> . Q. E. F. </p>
          </div>
          
          <div xml:id="elem.12.17" n="17">
            <head xml:id="ee-b12-Hd1e10712">PROPOSITION 17.</head>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e10715">
              <hi rend="ital">Given two spheres about the same centre</hi> , <hi rend="ital"> to
                inscribe in the greater sphere a polyhedral solid which does not touch the lesser
                sphere at its surface. </hi>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e10724"> Let two spheres be conceived about the same centre <hi rend="ital">A</hi> ; thus it
              is required to inscribe in the greater sphere a polyhedral solid which does not touch
              the lesser sphere at its surface. <!-- <figure/> -->
            </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e10732"> Let the spheres be cut by any plane through the centre; then the sections will be
              circles, inasmuch as the sphere was produced by the diameter remaining fixed and the
              semicircle being carried round it; [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e10734" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.11.def.14">XI.
                Def. 14</ref> ] hence, in whatever position we conceive the semicircle to be, the
              plane carried through it will produce a circle on the circumference of the sphere. </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e10738"> And it is manifest that this circle is the greatest possible,  inasmuch
              as the diameter of the sphere, which is of course the diameter both of the semicircle
              and of the circle, is greater than all the straight lines drawn across in the circle
              or the sphere. </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e10742"> Let then <hi rend="ital">BCDE</hi> be the circle in the greater sphere, and <hi rend="ital">FGH</hi> the circle in the lesser sphere; let two diameters in them, <hi rend="ital">BD</hi> , <hi rend="ital">CE</hi> , be drawn at right angles to one
              another; then, given the two circles <hi rend="ital">BCDE</hi> , <hi rend="ital">FGH</hi> about the same centre, let there be inscribed in the greater circle <hi rend="ital">BCDE</hi> an equilateral polygon with an even number of sides which does
              not touch the lesser circle <hi rend="ital">FGH</hi> , let <hi rend="ital">BK</hi> ,
                <hi rend="ital">KL</hi> , <hi rend="ital">LM</hi>
              <hi rend="ital">ME</hi> be its sides in the quadrant <hi rend="ital">BE</hi> . let <hi rend="ital">KA</hi> be joined and carried through to <hi rend="ital">N</hi> , let
                <hi rend="ital">AO</hi> be set up from the point <hi rend="ital">A</hi> at right
              angles to the plane of the circle <hi rend="ital">BCDE</hi> , and let it meet the
              surface of the sphere at <hi rend="ital">O</hi> , and through <hi rend="ital">AO</hi>
              and each of the straight lines <hi rend="ital">BD</hi> , <hi rend="ital">KN</hi> let
              planes be carried; they will then make greatest circles on the surface of the sphere,
              for the reason stated. </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e10814"> Let them make such, and in them let <hi rend="ital">BOD</hi> , <hi rend="ital">KON</hi> be the semicircles on <hi rend="ital">BD</hi> , <hi rend="ital">KN</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e10829"> Now, since <hi rend="ital">OA</hi> is at right angles to the plane of the circle <hi rend="ital">BCDE</hi> , therefore all the planes through <hi rend="ital">OA</hi> are
              also at right angles to the plane of the circle <hi rend="ital">BCDE</hi> ; [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e10843" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.11.18">XI. 18</ref> ] hence the semicircles <hi rend="ital">BOD</hi> , <hi rend="ital">KON</hi> are also at right angles to the
              plane of the circle <hi rend="ital">BCDE</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e10857"> And, since the semicircles <hi rend="ital">BED</hi> , <hi rend="ital">BOD</hi> , <hi rend="ital">KON</hi> are equal, for they are on the equal diameters <hi rend="ital">BD</hi> , <hi rend="ital">KN</hi> , therefore the quadrants <hi rend="ital">BE</hi>
              , <hi rend="ital">BO</hi> , <hi rend="ital">KO</hi> are also equal to one another. </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e10885"> Therefore there are as many straight lines in the quadrants <hi rend="ital">BO</hi>
              , <hi rend="ital">KO</hi> equal to the straight lines <hi rend="ital">BK</hi> , <hi rend="ital">KL</hi> , <hi rend="ital">LM</hi> , <hi rend="ital">ME</hi> as there are
              sides of the polygon in the quadrant <hi rend="ital">BE</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e10910"> Let them be inscribed, and let them be <hi rend="ital">BP</hi> , <hi rend="ital">PQ</hi> , <hi rend="ital">QR</hi> , <hi rend="ital">RO</hi> and <hi rend="ital">KS</hi> , <hi rend="ital">ST</hi> , <hi rend="ital">TU</hi> , <hi rend="ital">UO</hi> , let <hi rend="ital">SP</hi> , <hi rend="ital">TQ</hi> , <hi rend="ital">UR</hi> be joined,  and from <hi rend="ital">P</hi> , <hi rend="ital">S</hi> let perpendiculars be drawn to the plane of the circle <hi rend="ital">BCDE</hi> ; [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e10956" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.11.11">XI. 11</ref> ] these will fall
              on <hi rend="ital">BD</hi> , <hi rend="ital">KN</hi> , the common sections of the
              planes, inasmuch as the planes of <hi rend="ital">BOD</hi> , <hi rend="ital">KON</hi>
              are also at right angles to the plane of the circle <hi rend="ital">BCDE</hi> . [cf.
                <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e10975" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.11.def.4">XI. Def. 4</ref> ] </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e10980"> Let them so fall, and let them be <hi rend="ital">PV</hi> , <hi rend="ital">SW</hi>
              , and let <hi rend="ital">WV</hi> be joined. </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e10992"> Now since, in the equal semicircles <hi rend="ital">BOD</hi> , <hi rend="ital">KON</hi> , equal straight lines <hi rend="ital">BP</hi> , <hi rend="ital">KS</hi>
              have been cut off, and the perpendiculars <hi rend="ital">PV</hi> , <hi rend="ital">SW</hi> have been drawn, therefore <hi rend="ital">PV</hi> is equal to <hi rend="ital">SW</hi> , and <hi rend="ital">BV</hi> to <hi rend="ital">KW</hi> . [
                <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e11025" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.3.27">III. 27</ref> , <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e11029" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.1.26">I. 26</ref> ] </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e11033"> But the whole <hi rend="ital">BA</hi> is also equal to the whole <hi rend="ital">KA</hi> ; therefore the remainder <hi rend="ital">VA</hi> is also equal to the
              remainder <hi rend="ital">WA</hi> ; therefore, as <hi rend="ital">BV</hi> is to <hi rend="ital">VA</hi> , so is <hi rend="ital">KW</hi> to <hi rend="ital">WA</hi> ;
              therefore <hi rend="ital">WV</hi> is parallel to <hi rend="ital">KB</hi> . [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e11066" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.6.2">VI. 2</ref> ] </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e11070"> And, since each of the straight lines <hi rend="ital">PV</hi> , <hi rend="ital">SW</hi> is at right angles to the plane of the circle <hi rend="ital">BCDE</hi> ,
              therefore <hi rend="ital">PV</hi> is parallel to <hi rend="ital">SW</hi> . [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e11088" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.11.6">XI. 6</ref> ] </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e11092"> But it was also proved equal to it; therefore <hi rend="ital">WV</hi> , <hi rend="ital">SP</hi> are also equal and parallel. [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e11100" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.1.33">I. 33</ref> ] </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e11104"> And, since <hi rend="ital">WV</hi> is parallel to <hi rend="ital">SP</hi> , while
                <hi rend="ital">WV</hi> is parallel to <hi rend="ital">KB</hi> , therefore <hi rend="ital">SP</hi> is also parallel to <hi rend="ital">KB</hi> . [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e11125" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.11.9">XI. 9</ref> ] </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e11130"> And <hi rend="ital">BP</hi> , <hi rend="ital">KS</hi> join their extremities;
              therefore the quadrilateral <hi rend="ital">KBPS</hi> is in one plane, inasmuch as, if
              two straight lines be parallel, and points be taken at random on each of them, the
              straight line joining the points is in the same plane with the parallels. [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e11141" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.11.7">XI. 7</ref> ] </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e11145"> For the same reason each of the quadrilaterals <hi rend="ital">SPQT</hi> , <hi rend="ital">TQRU</hi> is also in one plane. </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e11154"> But the triangle <hi rend="ital">URO</hi> is also in one plane. [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e11159" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.11.2">XI. 2</ref> ] </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e11163"> If then we conceive straight lines joined from the points <hi rend="ital">P</hi> ,
                <hi rend="ital">S</hi> , <hi rend="ital">Q</hi> , <hi rend="ital">T</hi> , <hi rend="ital">R</hi> , <hi rend="ital">U</hi> to <hi rend="ital">A</hi> , there will
              be constructed a certain polyhedral solid figure between the circumferences <hi rend="ital">BO</hi> , <hi rend="ital">KO</hi> , consisting of pyramids of which the
              quadrilaterals <hi rend="ital">KBPS</hi> , <hi rend="ital">SPQT</hi> , <hi rend="ital">TQRU</hi> and the triangle <hi rend="ital">URO</hi> are the bases and the point <hi rend="ital">A</hi> the vertex. 
            </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e11210"> And, if we make the same construction in the case of each of the sides <hi rend="ital">KL</hi> , <hi rend="ital">LM</hi> , <hi rend="ital">ME</hi> as in the
              case of <hi rend="ital">BK</hi> , and further in the case of the remaining three
              quadrants, there will be constructed a certain polyhedral figure inscribed in the
              sphere and contained by pyramids, of which the said quadrilaterals and the triangle
                <hi rend="ital">URO</hi> , and the others corresponding to them, are the bases and
              the point <hi rend="ital">A</hi> the vertex. </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e11232"> I say that the said polyhedron will not touch the lesser sphere at the surface on
              which the circle <hi rend="ital">FGH</hi> is. </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e11239"> Let <hi rend="ital">AX</hi> be drawn from the point <hi rend="ital">A</hi>
              perpendicular to the plane of the quadrilateral <hi rend="ital">KBPS</hi> , and let it
              meet the plane at the point <hi rend="ital">X</hi> ; [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e11253" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.11.11">XI. 11</ref> ] let <hi rend="ital">XB</hi> , <hi rend="ital">XK</hi>
              be joined. </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e11264"> Then, since <hi rend="ital">AX</hi> is at right angles to the plane of the
              quadrilateral <hi rend="ital">KBPS</hi> , therefore it is also at right angles to all
              the straight lines which meet it and are in the plane of the quadrilateral. [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e11272" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.11.def.3">XI. Def. 3</ref> ] </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e11276"> Therefore <hi rend="ital">AX</hi> is at right angles to each of the straight lines
                <hi rend="ital">BX</hi> , <hi rend="ital">XK</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e11288"> And, since <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> is equal to <hi rend="ital">AK</hi> , the square
              on <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> is also equal to the square on <hi rend="ital">AK</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e11303"> And the squares on <hi rend="ital">AX</hi> , <hi rend="ital">XB</hi> are equal to
              the square on <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> , for the angle at <hi rend="ital">X</hi> is
              right; [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e11317" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.1.47">I. 47</ref> ] and the squares on <hi rend="ital">AX</hi> , <hi rend="ital">XK</hi> are equal to the square on <hi rend="ital">AK</hi> . [ <hi rend="ital">id</hi> .] </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e11334"> Therefore the squares on <hi rend="ital">AX</hi> , <hi rend="ital">XB</hi> are equal
              to the squares on <hi rend="ital">AX</hi> , <hi rend="ital">XK</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e11350"> Let the square on <hi rend="ital">AX</hi> be subtracted from each; therefore the
              remainder, the square on <hi rend="ital">BX</hi> , is equal to the remainder, the
              square on <hi rend="ital">XK</hi> ; therefore <hi rend="ital">BX</hi> is equal to <hi rend="ital">XK</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e11368"> Similarly we can prove that the straight lines joined from <hi rend="ital">X</hi> to
                <hi rend="ital">P</hi> , <hi rend="ital">S</hi> are equal to each of the straight
              lines <hi rend="ital">BX</hi> , <hi rend="ital">XK</hi> . 
            </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e11386"> Therefore the circle described with centre <hi rend="ital">X</hi> and distance one
              of the straight lines <hi rend="ital">XB</hi> , <hi rend="ital">XK</hi> will pass
              through <hi rend="ital">P</hi> , <hi rend="ital">S</hi> also, and <hi rend="ital">KBPS</hi> will be a quadrilateral in a circle. </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e11408"> Now, since <hi rend="ital">KB</hi> is greater than <hi rend="ital">WV</hi> , while
                <hi rend="ital">WV</hi> is equal to <hi rend="ital">SP</hi> , therefore <hi rend="ital">KB</hi> is greater than <hi rend="ital">SP</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e11430"> But <hi rend="ital">KB</hi> is equal to each of the straight lines <hi rend="ital">KS</hi> , <hi rend="ital">BP</hi> ; therefore each of the straight lines <hi rend="ital">KS</hi> , <hi rend="ital">BP</hi> is greater than <hi rend="ital">SP</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e11452"> And, since <hi rend="ital">KBPS</hi> is a quadrilateral in a circle, and <hi rend="ital">KB</hi> , <hi rend="ital">BP</hi> , <hi rend="ital">KS</hi> are equal,
              and <hi rend="ital">PS</hi> less, and <hi rend="ital">BX</hi> is the radius of the
              circle, therefore the square on <hi rend="ital">KB</hi> is greater than double of the
              square on <hi rend="ital">BX</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e11481"> Let <hi rend="ital">KZ</hi> be drawn from <hi rend="ital">K</hi> perpendicular to
                <hi rend="ital">BV</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e11493"> Then, since <hi rend="ital">BD</hi> is less than double of <hi rend="ital">DZ</hi> ,
              and, as <hi rend="ital">BD</hi> is to <hi rend="ital">DZ</hi> , so is the rectangle
                <hi rend="ital">DB</hi> , <hi rend="ital">BZ</hi> to the rectangle <hi rend="ital">DZ</hi> , <hi rend="ital">ZB</hi> , if a square be described upon <hi rend="ital">BZ</hi> and the parallelogram on <hi rend="ital">ZD</hi> be completed, then the
              rectangle <hi rend="ital">DB</hi> , <hi rend="ital">BZ</hi> is also less than double
              of the rectangle <hi rend="ital">DZ</hi> , <hi rend="ital">ZB</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e11540"> And, if <hi rend="ital">KD</hi> be joined, the rectangle <hi rend="ital">DB</hi> ,
                <hi rend="ital">BZ</hi> is equal to the square on <hi rend="ital">BK</hi> , and the
              rectangle <hi rend="ital">DZ</hi> , <hi rend="ital">ZB</hi> equal to the square on <hi rend="ital">KZ</hi> ; [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e11564" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.3.31">III. 31</ref> , <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e11567" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.6.8 elem.6.8.p.1">VI. 8 and Por.</ref> ] therefore the
              square on <hi rend="ital">KB</hi> is less than double of the square on <hi rend="ital">KZ</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e11577"> But the square on <hi rend="ital">KB</hi> is greater than double of the square on
                <hi rend="ital">BX</hi> ; therefore the square on <hi rend="ital">KZ</hi> is greater
              than the square on <hi rend="ital">BX</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e11592"> And, since <hi rend="ital">BA</hi> is equal to <hi rend="ital">KA</hi> , the square
              on <hi rend="ital">BA</hi> is equal to the square on <hi rend="ital">AK</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e11607"> And the squares on <hi rend="ital">BX</hi> , <hi rend="ital">XA</hi> are equal to
              the square on <hi rend="ital">BA</hi> , and the squares on <hi rend="ital">KZ</hi> ,
                <hi rend="ital">ZA</hi> equal to the square on <hi rend="ital">KA</hi> ; [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e11628" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.1.47">I. 47</ref> ] therefore the squares on <hi rend="ital">BX</hi> , <hi rend="ital">XA</hi> are equal to the squares on <hi rend="ital">KZ</hi> , <hi rend="ital">ZA</hi> ,  and of these the
              square on <hi rend="ital">KZ</hi> is greater than the square on <hi rend="ital">BX</hi> ; therefore the remainder, the square on <hi rend="ital">ZA</hi> , is less
              than the square on <hi rend="ital">XA</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e11658"> Therefore <hi rend="ital">AX</hi> is greater than <hi rend="ital">AZ</hi> ;
              therefore <hi rend="ital">AX</hi> is much greater than <hi rend="ital">AG</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e11673"> And <hi rend="ital">AX</hi> is the perpendicular on one base of the polyhedron, and
                <hi rend="ital">AG</hi> on the surface of the lesser sphere; hence the polyhedron
              will not touch the lesser sphere on its surface. </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e11682"> Therefore, given two spheres about the same centre, a polyhedral solid has been
              inscribed in the greater sphere which does not touch the lesser sphere at its surface.
              Q. E. F. </p>
            <div xml:id="elem.12.17.p.1" type="porism" org="uniform" sample="complete">
              <head xml:id="ee-b12-Hd1e11687">PORISM.</head>
              <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e11690"> But if in another sphere also a polyhedral solid be inscribed similar to the solid
                in the sphere <hi rend="ital">BCDE</hi> , the polyhedral solid in the sphere <hi rend="ital">BCDE</hi> has to the polyhedral solid in the other sphere the ratio
                triplicate of that which the diameter of the sphere <hi rend="ital">BCDE</hi> has to
                the diameter of the other sphere. </p>
              <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e11702"> For, the solids being divided into their pyramids similar in multitude and
                arrangement, the pyramids will be similar. </p>
              <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e11705"> But similar pyramids are to one another in the triplicate ratio of their
                corresponding sides; [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e11707" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.12.8.p.1">XII. 8, Por.</ref>
                ] therefore the pyramid of which the quadrilateral <hi rend="ital">KBPS</hi> is the
                base, and the point <hi rend="ital">A</hi> the vertex, has to the similarly arranged
                pyramid in the other sphere the ratio triplicate of that which the corresponding
                side has to the corresponding side, that is, of that which the radius <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> of the sphere about <hi rend="ital">A</hi> as centre has to
                the radius of the other sphere. </p>
              <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e11723"> Similarly also each pyramid of those in the sphere about <hi rend="ital">A</hi> as
                centre has to each similarly arranged pyramid of those in the other sphere the ratio
                triplicate of that which <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> has to the radius of the other
                sphere. </p>
              <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e11733"> And, as one of the antecedents is to one of the consequents, so are all the
                antecedents to all the consequents; [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e11735" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.5.12">V.
                  12</ref> ]  hence the whole polyhedral solid in the sphere about <hi rend="ital">A</hi> as centre has to the whole polyhedral solid in the other sphere
                the ratio triplicate of that which <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> has to the radius of the
                other sphere, that is, of that which the diameter <hi rend="ital">BD</hi> has to the
                diameter of the other sphere. Q. E. D. </p>
            </div>
          </div>
          <div xml:id="elem.12.18" n="18">
            <head xml:id="ee-b12-Hd1e11752">PROPOSITION 18.</head>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e11755">
              <hi rend="ital"> Spheres are to one another in the triplicate ratio of their
                respective diameters. </hi>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e11761"> Let the spheres <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> , <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi> be conceived,
              and let <hi rend="ital">BC</hi> , <hi rend="ital">EF</hi> be their diameters; I say
              that the sphere <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> has to the sphere <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi>
              the ratio triplicate of that which <hi rend="ital">BC</hi> has to <hi rend="ital">EF</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e11789"> For, if the sphere <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> has not to the sphere <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi> the ratio triplicate of that which <hi rend="ital">BC</hi> has to <hi rend="ital">EF</hi> , then the sphere <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> will have either to
              some less sphere than the sphere <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi> , or to a greater, the ratio
              triplicate of that which <hi rend="ital">BC</hi> has to <hi rend="ital">EF</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e11817"> First, let it have that ratio to a less sphere <hi rend="ital">GHK</hi> , let <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi> be conceived about the same centre with <hi rend="ital">GHK</hi> , let there be inscribed in the greater sphere <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi> a
              polyhedral solid which does not touch the lesser sphere <hi rend="ital">GHK</hi> at
              its surface, [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e11835" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.12.17">XII. 17</ref> ] 
              and let there also be inscribed in the sphere <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> a polyhedral
              solid similar to the polyhedral solid in the sphere <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi> ;
              therefore the polyhedral solid in <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> has to the polyhedral solid
              in <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi> the ratio triplicate of that which <hi rend="ital">BC</hi>
              has to <hi rend="ital">EF</hi> . [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e11857" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.12.17.p.1">XII. 17,
                Por.</ref> ] <!-- <figure/> -->
            </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e11864"> But the sphere <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> also has to the sphere <hi rend="ital">GHK</hi> the ratio triplicate of that which <hi rend="ital">BC</hi> has to <hi rend="ital">EF</hi> ; therefore, as the sphere <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> is to the
              sphere <hi rend="ital">GHK</hi> , so is the polyhedral solid in the sphere <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> to the polyhedral solid in the sphere <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi>
              ; and, alternately, as the sphere <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> is to the polyhedron in it,
              so is the sphere <hi rend="ital">GHK</hi> to the polyhedral solid in the sphere <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi> . [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e11901" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.5.16">V. 16</ref> ] </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e11905"> But the sphere <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> is greater than the polyhedron in it;
              therefore the sphere <hi rend="ital">GHK</hi> is also greater than the polyhedron in
              the sphere <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e11917">But it is also less, for it is enclosed by it.</p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e11920"> Therefore the sphere <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> has not to a less sphere than the
              sphere <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi> the ratio triplicate of that which the diameter <hi rend="ital">BC</hi> has to <hi rend="ital">EF</hi> . 
            </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e11935"> Similarly we can prove that neither has the sphere <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi> to a
              less sphere than the sphere <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> the ratio triplicate of that
              which <hi rend="ital">EF</hi> has to <hi rend="ital">BC</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e11950"> I say next that neither has the sphere <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> to any greater
              sphere than the sphere <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi> the ratio triplicate of that which <hi rend="ital">BC</hi> has to <hi rend="ital">EF</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e11966"> For, if possible, let it have that ratio to a greater, <hi rend="ital">LMN</hi> ;
              therefore, inversely, the sphere <hi rend="ital">LMN</hi> has to the sphere <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> the ratio triplicate of that which the diameter <hi rend="ital">EF</hi> has to the diameter <hi rend="ital">BC</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e11984"> But, inasmuch as <hi rend="ital">LMN</hi> is greater than <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi> ,
              therefore, as the sphere <hi rend="ital">LMN</hi> is to the sphere <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> , so is the sphere <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi> to some less sphere than the
              sphere <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> , as was before proved. [ <ref xml:id="ee-b12-Rd1e12005" target="http://scta.info/resource/elem.12.2.l.1">XII. 2, Lemma</ref> ] </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e12009"> Therefore the sphere <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi> also has to some less sphere than the
              sphere <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> the ratio triplicate of that which <hi rend="ital">EF</hi> has to <hi rend="ital">BC</hi> : which was proved impossible. </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e12024"> Therefore the sphere <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> has not to any sphere greater than the
              sphere <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi> the ratio triplicate of that which <hi rend="ital">BC</hi> has to <hi rend="ital">EF</hi> . </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e12039"> But it was proved that neither has it that ratio to a less sphere. </p>
            <p xml:id="ee-b12-d1e12042"> Therefore the sphere <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> has to the sphere <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi> the ratio triplicate of that which <hi rend="ital">BC</hi> has to <hi rend="ital">EF</hi> . Q. E. D. </p>
          </div>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>